<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letters to a sick friend containing such observations as may render the use of remedies effectual towards the removal of sickness, and preservation of health. By J. M.</title>
            <author>Marlow, John, 1648-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51992</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M691A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217455</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829120</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829120</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33556</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51992)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33556)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1917:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Letters to a sick friend containing such observations as may render the use of remedies effectual towards the removal of sickness, and preservation of health. By J. M.</title>
                  <author>Marlow, John, 1648-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.A. for Thomas Parkhurst at the Bible and Three Crowns at the lower end of Cheapside, near Mercers Chappel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank. Title page is A2.</note>
                  <note>Running title: Letters to a sick friend tending to health.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Health promotion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Health --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33556:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LETTERS TO A Sick Friend, CONTAINING SUCH OBSERVATIONS AS MAY Render the Uſe of Remedies Effectual towards The Removal of SICKNESS, AND PRESERVATION OF HEALTH.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. A.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chappel,</hi> 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33556:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33556:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33556:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33556:3"/>
            <head>The PUBLISHERS EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe ingenuous and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Letters being ſent me at ſeveral times, and upon par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Occaſions, from the City of <hi>London,</hi> into the Countrey, I thought them very well deſerving to be expoſed to publick View, as containing moſt neceſſary Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations
<pb facs="tcp:33556:4"/>tending to Health and long Life, with the Way to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Remedies Effectual: A Theme I do not remember I ever ſaw in Print before. The Subject is Great and Noble, and the Style is ſmooth and pleaſant, and accommodate to the Genius of this Age: And I am of Opinion, that if the Divine and Phyſical Intimations given in theſe Letters, were improved to Practice, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Remedies would very ſeldom fail of ſucceſs, and moſt men might arrive unto a very great Age, and their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage through this World would be much more Eaſie and Comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than which nothing can be more deſirable. I heartily wiſh
<pb facs="tcp:33556:4"/>they may be as Delightful and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful to thee in Print, as they were to me and ſome others in Manuſcript; and then I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced for the Publication, and ſhall more eaſily obtain the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Pardon for thus Reading them aloud to the whole World.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:33556:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33556:5"/>
            <head>LETTERS TO A Sick Friend TENDING TO HEALTH.</head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours dated the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth inſtant, wherein you give me an account of the loſs of your Health, and alſo requeſt me to give you ſuch prudential Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33556:6"/>as may tend towards your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery. Sir, you know my Service is alwayes at your Beck; but I muſt take leave to tell you, that I cannot ſerve you better in ſuch a deplorable Diſtemper as yours is, than to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to take the Advice of your able and Learned Phyſician, whoſe Preſcriptions have ſo often been attended with ſucceſs. Need I uſe Arguments to perſwade a wiſe man to endeavour to reſtore his Health? Sir, your Health is highly valuable upon a <hi>publick</hi> as well as upon a <hi>private</hi> account, it being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient unto the good of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities as well as of particular perſons. A whole Fleet hath been diſabled for two Months by the Indiſpoſition of the Admiral, and two Towns loſt by the Governour falling ill in the time of the Sieges. Accidents of Health ſometimes become Accidents
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33556:6"/>of State; and the pulſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſometimes beats high or low with that of the Governor. Health is that which makes all our Delights delightfull. A ſound Mind in a ſound Body, conſummates the perfection of Humane Nature. The Health of the Body conduceth unto the Harmony of the Soul, and the Harmony of the Soul preſerves the Health of the Body: It preſerves the Faculties of the Mind in ſtrength and vigor, clears the Underſtanding, makes the Wit acute, and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory retentive. Without Health the moſt delicious Dainties will not pleaſe the Pallate, the moſt fragrant Odors will not delight the Smell, the moſt harmonious Melodies will not gratifie the Ear, the moſt beautiful Object will not pleaſe the Eye, nor the ſofteſt Down eaſe the Bones. When mens fleſh upon them is in pain, it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33556:7"/>makes their Souls within them to mourn. Health is that which is of moſt Comfortable Importance next unto the Salvation of the Souls of men; eſpecially when we conſider what a multitude of Diſtempers the mortal Bodies of men are expoſed unto. Some Phyſicians have found two hundred in that ſmall and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part the Eye. Our bodies are like a Curious Inſtrument of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſtrings; and it's very wonderful if one or more of thoſe ſtrings be not out of tune. It were a great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, if it were the pleaſure of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to give men a conſtant frame of Health during their pilgrimage, and might very deſervedly be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned amongſt the Catalogue of our Mercies, to have our bodies like the <hi>Jews</hi> bodies in the Wilderneſs, little worn or impaired by pining ſickneſſes. If the Woman in the Goſpel had
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33556:7"/>ſpent all her ſubſtance upon any thing but the ineſtimable Jewel of her Health, ſhe had not gone out of our Saviours preſence without a Reprehenſion. If men did but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the wonderfull compoſure of their bodies, the ſituation of the parts, the circulation of the blood, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Meanders of the Veins and Nerves, and the curious diſtribution of our Aliment into Fleſh and Blood, they would then admire that every Obſtruction did not ſtop their breath, and that the leaſt Inflamation did not ſend them out of the World as in a fiery Chariot, and that the leaſt Degree of putrefaction did not crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them into their firſt Original; ſo that inſtead of wondering they live no more in health, they would think it ſtrange they live one hour in eaſe. All our good things may be reduced into thoſe of the Mind,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33556:8"/>of the Body, and of Fortune; which three if enjoyed, render a man as happy as <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his Glory. He that hath Health to enjoy his Riches, Grace to preſerve his Health, and the hope of Glory to remune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate his Grace, needs no more. When a healthy Conſtitution and a holy Diſpoſition joyn hand in hand, they compleat our Happineſs. Health without Religion is but like a Down Pillow to a Reſtleſs Head, which the beſt Chamberlain cannot make eaſie: And Riches without Health is but like Meat without a Stomach, which the beſt Cook cannot make reliſhing. Reſtauration to health is a Kind of Reſurrection, and it's call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by St. <hi>James</hi> a Raiſing up. When the Organs of our bodies are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned, and our Spirits are waſted by Sickneſs, our Souls cannot act with Vivacity; our teeming Invention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33556:8"/>barren, our ſoaring Fancy droops and hangs the wing, and the remembrance of things paſs away as water through a Sieve; Mens parts and abilities being according unto the number, activity and orderly motion of their Spirits; and they are more or leſs pure and regular, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto the Healthy Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Blood and Humors.</p>
               <p>When the golden Bole is broken, and the ſound of the Grinding is low, and the Pitcher is broken at the Fountain, and the Wheel broken at the Ceſtern, then the Sun and the Moon and the Stars will be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Were it poſſible for a man to ſtand upon one of the Battlements of Heaven, and with one glance of his Eye to behold all the Wounds and Diſeaſes, all the Groans and Complaints of Dying Mortals, how would Health and Eaſe be prized
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33556:9"/>by ſuch a one? But Health is never ſo much prized, as when it brings Letters of Recommendation from Sickneſs. But, Sir, that your Pulſe may beat harmoniouſly, and your Blood circulate regularly to extream old Age, is the Wiſh of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your intirely affectionate Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER II.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours, dated the tenth inſtant, wherein you give me an account of your reception of the laſt Remedies I ſent you; but I am ſorry to hear you ſhould be guilty of ſo great a Miſtake, as to think that no
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33556:9"/>Obſervation of yours can render the uſe of Medicines ſubſervient towards Health and long Life. Sir, I pray give me leave to aſſert the contrary, and to prove, that the practice of Piety and true Religion, have a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful tendency towards long Life. If you deſire to wear a Crown of Glory in this World and the next alſo, it may be obtained by gray Hairs found in the Way of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: And you know it's promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as a Bleſſing to the Good man, <hi>that he ſhall come to his Grave in a full Age,</hi> as a <hi>Shock of Corn comes in its ſeaſon.</hi> The beloved Diſciple of our Lord ſurvived the other Diſciples; and many of the Fathers of the Church were long-lived: Which ſhews that the Bleſſing of long Life, ſo often promiſed under the Law, had leſs abatement after our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours dayes than other Bleſſings had,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33556:10"/>
                  <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> never Dyed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Examples that a ſpotleſs Life might poſſibly have been Immortal, as it is probable that Man before his Fall was: Yet had he never ſinned, perhaps he had not ſtill remained here upon Earth; though his Age might have been extended to ſome thouſands of years, and at length have been tranſlated from hence to Heaven, where he could neither have ſinned nor dyed.</p>
               <p>When our great and wiſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor made Man the Maſterpiece of his Creation, he was pleaſed as an expreſſion of his Kindneſs to plant him in a Garden, wherein he might have an opportunity at the ſame time both to Contemplate his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Goodneſs, and to preſerve his own Life; being furniſht with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Wiſdom, he could diſcern the particular Qualities of thoſe Plants
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33556:10"/>with which he converſed: But Man being too familiar with the Tree of Knowledge, forfeited his Right unto the Tree of Life, and hath expoſed himſelf unto the aſſaults of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Diſeaſes. But ſuch is the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heaven unto Man in his lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſtate, that he is pleaſed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſome of the Influences of this Symbolical Tree, upon his Obedience unto the Divine Will: So that by our Obſervance of the Eternal Laws of Evangelical Purity, which are preſcribed as the Chriſtians Rule, we may as it were tranſplant the Tree of Life into our own Gardens, and ſit under the ſhadow thereof with great Delight, and its fruit may become ſweet unto our taſte: There are certain practices which have a great tendency towards long Life; and this the inſpired Penman intimates when he ſaith, <hi>Righteouſneſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33556:11"/>tendeth to life;</hi> and there are frequent Promiſes of long Life made to the Obedient. <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſurvived all the <hi>Jews</hi> who came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the reſt were not ſuffered to ſee <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> leſt they ſhould introduce <hi>Egy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptian</hi> Innovations. Nothing doth more conduce unto the preſervation of our natural Health, than our living the Divine Life; but when our Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations and Actions are wholly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about the Gratifications of the Animal Life, we do but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for the Meſſenger of the Grave. The practice of ſerious Chriſtianity is a great friend unto the Health of Humane Nature. The circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial actions of Religion are very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluential towards the lengthning mens Lives; as the ſweet ſleep of tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate perſons, their freedom from violent and enraged Paſſions, with the admirable Contentment that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33556:11"/>dwells in a holy Conſcience; alſo the great Moderation that's exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſuch Perſons. There are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the Divine Life leiſurely Contemplations of Heavenly things, Joyes refined from the Dregs of Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, Hopes of a noble and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous nature, wholſom, ſweet and comfortable Fears, and a univerſal Harmony in the Mind. Theſe things make the Lamp of Life burn bright and clear; and from hence by the favour of Divine Clemency Health ſpringeth forth ſpeedily. <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>'s Obſervation is excellent, <hi>That all the Pleaſures of the Body proceed from the Joy of the Mind:</hi> The breaking off our ſins by Righteouſneſs, many times proves a lengthening of our temporal Tranquility. The Jewiſh Doctors ſay, That <hi>Adam</hi> felt no Cold notwithſtanding he was naked, becauſe he had Communion with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33556:12"/>God; but as ſoon as ever he had eaten the forbidden Fruit, his Head aked. Faith and Obedience, like the Tree of Life in Paradiſe, not only Sacramentally but really conduce unto Health and long Life, ſo far as it is a Bleſſing; and this it doth by impregnating our Food with the tincture of a Divine Benediction, by meliorating our Conſtitutions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing wholſom Diſpoſitions in the Air, and Friendly Influences in the Hoſt of Heaven. The <hi>Jews</hi> came under a Promiſe of having their Bread and their Water bleſſed, and Sickneſs removed, if they obeyed the Divine Law: And <hi>Solomon</hi> urgeth the conſideration of our Health as a ſtrong Argument to promote holy and Religious Fear; telling us it ſhould <hi>be health unto our Navels, and marrow to our Bones:</hi> And <hi>Godlineſs hath the promiſe of the Life that now is,</hi> as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33556:12"/>well as of that which is to come: If men love Life, and deſire many dayes, and make it their requeſt to obtain the Divine Wiſdom, the way preſcribed is to deſiſt from evil, and to <hi>do good,</hi> and then <hi>length of dayes and long life</hi> ſhall be added, as the Wiſeſt of men obſerved. Yielding Subjection unto the Father of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, is as ſure a way to obtain the Bleſſing of Health and long Life as Obedience unto our natural Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; for there is a Command with a Promiſe annexed unto both. And we find Life in the Inventory of a Chriſtians goods, when drawn up by the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles. And the inſpired Pen-men frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſcribe Religion as an Antidote againſt immature Death, it being a direct Enemy unto Sin which brought in Sickneſs. True goodneſs doth as well conduce to the prolongation of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33556:13"/>the Body in natural Life, as to its Immortality in Eternal Life; and the Body hath the perfection of Life, <hi>viz.</hi> Health from the Soul, as well as Life it ſelf: Dying unto ſin is an excellent means to preſerve Life, if men would try the Experiment, and endeavour to procure the Divine Providence to be their Life-Guard. We live by the Word of Bleſſing out of the Mouth of God; every Command, if obſerved, like Food and Phyſick tends unto the lengthening our Dayes: Now although it be a known truth, that of our ſelves we can do nothing; yet it is as true, that by the Grace of God we may do much in the practice of Religion, and conſequently may contribute to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the lengthening of our Dayes, and rendering the uſe of Medicines effectual towards that great and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble end. Moreover, Religion ſecures
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33556:13"/>Men from the Terrors of a guilty Conſcience, which many times makes Men waſh their Hands in their own blood; and it alſo preſerves Men from the Condemnation of Humane Tribunals, many being cut off by the Hand of Juſtice, for their flagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious impieties, as Murders, Thefts and Rapines. But Sir, that the great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of Men may ſo ballance the Humours in your Body, that you may live to ſee the accompliſhment of all your good Wiſhes, is the hearty Wiſh of him who hath no more time left at preſent, than to tell you that he is and will be</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours in the moſt unreſerved Reſpects. <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33556:14"/>
               <head>LETTER III</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THis comes to Kiſs your Hand, and to make an Inquiry af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the happy Succeſs of the laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, and alſo to encourage your Perſeverance in their uſe, although you do not preſently find them anſwer your expectation: for I hope you do not expect Medicines to Operate meerly by their natural Energy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into them at their firſt Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo know that their effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy doth depend primarily upon the Pleaſure of the Divine Will, who hath limited the periods of humane Life: We Live not at an Adventure, but the manner and Moments of our Life and Death come under a Divine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, and the ſucceſs of all Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33556:14"/>depends upon the peculiar Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Heaven. The moſt Infallible way to have our Diſtempers remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, is to endeavour to procure the concourſe of that Divine Influence, and to engage the Soveraign Power of that Almighty Healer, unto whom belong the Iſſues from Death. Though our Lord was not corporally preſent with <hi>Lazarus,</hi> yet he knew without Creature Intelligence that he was Dead, and told his Diſciples ſo; God alſo told <hi>Samuel</hi> that <hi>Moſes</hi> was Dead. It matters not who Plants or Waters, if God denies to give the Increaſe. The Divine Favour is the beſt Skreen to ſhelter men from the innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Accidents of Humane Life, in which every Minute we are Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with a Thouſand Deaths and dangers. When the great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of Men withdraws his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, we are left expoſed to the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33556:15"/>malignant Aſpects of Planets, to the fatal Contingencies of Wars and Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, and are indanger'd by every Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident; the Duſt of a Wheel, the fall of a Tile, the largeneſs of a Morſel, the Laſh of a Whip, the unevenneſs of a Stone, the Plenty of a Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, may ſtop our Breath. It is a confeſt truth, that every natural mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath its beginning, duration and period, dependent on the pleaſure of the firſt Mover: now the Life of Man being a nutural motion, our Nativity and Death are both order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that Omnipotent Agent, in whom we live, move, and have our being. The Diſciples themſelves could not cure Diſeaſes at all times, if they could, St. <hi>Paul</hi> would not have left <hi>Trophimus</hi> Sick at <hi>Miletum,</hi> nor have Sorrowed ſo much for <hi>Epaphroditus</hi>'s Sickneſs. The Life of Man conſiſting in a requiſite Harmony of Qualities,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33556:15"/>and in a due commixture of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Heat and radical moiſture, which Harmony is more or leſs, according unto the more or leſs exquiſite tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament of Body aſſigned unto each ſingle Perſon, by the free diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Divine Will, it muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that the continuance of every man in this natural Life, depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the pleaſure of him who hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined our Days, numbered our Months, and ſet our Bounds, which we cannot paſs without his leave who gave us the durability of our temperaments, and compaſſed our pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods within the Circle of his ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Providence. To imagine the Life of Man fixt beyond the poſſibility of being prolonged or ſhortened by an Almighty pleaſure, ſeems highly unreaſonable; becauſe he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a power in his own Hands to contract or prorogue as he pleaſeth;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33556:16"/>Sometimes Divine Wiſdom beſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own Reaſons, doth reſolve the Death of ſome Perſons, and then the moſt proper Remedies are uſed in vain, either towards the removal of Sickneſs, or the preſervation of Health. The univerſal Conſerver of all things, takes notice of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal and ſubſequent Cauſes of things, Governing, Diſpoſing and Ordering according unto his own free Will, and yet his Government is void of any fatal Violence, and comes to an efficiency from the ordination of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious natural cauſes and humane elections, which prove the occaſions of ſupporting or deſtroying Life. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine goodneſs doth not aboliſh, but Diſpoſeth of future Contingencies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out nulling the freedom of the Agent; he moderates and governs Events ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his pleaſure, and yet ſuffers the Creature to exerciſe its own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33556:16"/>motions. The rage of Men and Devils cannot accelerate the motions of Divine Providence. A Sparrow doth not fall to the ground, much leſs a man into the Grave, without a Divine Permiſſion. The Manner and Moments of our death are not the effects of Contingency: <hi>To God the Lord belongs the Iſſues from death,</hi> or in the Original, <hi>the Inlets to Death,</hi> viz. Diſeaſes. Natural Remedies are but like <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Staffe layd upon the dead Child, they will not help unleſs a ſupernatural vertue concurs. The <hi>Egy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptians</hi> in their Temples had a remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Hieroglyphick, A Young man, an Old man, and a Hawk in the middle: Intimating, the Beginning and Period of humane Life depends upon the Influence of divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s death might ſeem the effect of Juvenile raſhneſs in War, but it conduced towards the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33556:17"/>of <hi>Huldah's</hi> Prophecy. The Advice of the <hi>Philiſtine</hi> Diviners is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obſervable: When the People were ſmitten with Hemorrhoids, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the offering up of golden He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morroids, thinking by that myſtical Remedy to appeaſe the Diſpleaſure of Heaven; and to intimate, that they thought the beſt of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance not valuable, to purchaſe Health; but chiefly to repreſent their Belief that the Cure of Diſeaſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended upon a divine Influence.</p>
               <p>Many ſmart the longer under the Rod of God, becauſe they eye not the Hand that moves it. The Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins ſay, when <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s Hand wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd, the falſe Prophets told him it came by Chance, thereby to divert his reflections from the firſt Cauſe. Some have obſerved, that the beſt way to cure the Kings-Evil is by the Stroak of the Kings Hand; and ſure the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33556:17"/>beſt way to remove the ſmart of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers inflicted by the Hand of God, is to conſider that it is his Hand: No man knows, when Divine Providence, who hath the Pen in his Hand, and writes down the Days and Actions of our Lives, will be pleaſed to ſet a Comma of Afflictions, or a Period of Death. The Weights and Plummets of Mans reſtleſs Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, cannot make the Clock of Gods appointed time ſtrike one Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute ſooner than he hath ſet it: And he only hath appointed how many tedious Dayes and weariſome Nights we ſhall have, before the bright Morning of Eternity dawn upon us. The reaſon why Natural Remedies do many times prove ineffectual, is becauſe there is a Determinate ſeaſon wherein all Perſons and things muſt have their final iſſue. Thus we find <hi>Moſes</hi> died the Year before the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33556:18"/>entred into <hi>Canaan: Daniel</hi> ſome few Years before the Foundation of the Temple: And <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt in the firſt Year of the Baptiſm of our bleſſed Saviour, when the Goſpel he began to preach, was to be publiſhed in its Glory: At their ſeaſons they muſt go their wayes to reſt, and lie down until they receive their lot at the end of Dayes. If God had not the Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of the Lives of Men in his own Hands, what miſerable confuſions would there be in the World? If <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great had been ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Cradle, how could the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies of <hi>Daniel</hi> have been fulfilled concerning him? The <hi>Jews</hi> could not prejudice the Life of the Lord of Life, until that hour which was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be his laſt hour was come: For, as it is appointed <hi>once</hi> to Die, ſo alſo <hi>when</hi> to Die: and that you may enjoy a Long and Healthful
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33556:18"/>Life, and at laſt a happy Eternity, is the prayer of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your humble Servant, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER IV.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Joyfully entertained the welcome News of the good ſucceſs of your laſt Remedies, but am ſorry to find you attribute all to Neceſſity; as if becauſe the Period of Humane Life is appointed, and the ſucceſs of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines depends upon a Supernatural Concourſe; therefore to inferr, we cannot be acceſſary towards the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our own Dayes. Sir, it is a fond Opinion, and a great miſtake ſo to think: for the <hi>Jews</hi> were wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly inſtrumental in taking away the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33556:19"/>Life of the Lord of Life, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they did nothing but what Divine goodneſs had determined be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be done. The Prophet told <hi>Amaziah,</hi> he knew God had Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to deſtroy him, and yet he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo tells him, that he was inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal towards his own Death, in not hearkning unto the Voyce of the Lord. <hi>Eli</hi>'s Sons diſobedience pronounced the Sentence of Death againſt them; and it is rendred as the reaſon why God had reſolved to ſlay them. The Date of the Old Worlds Duration was fixed to one Hundred and twenty Years; Yet we find it not ſo long-liv'd by twenty Years; their wickedneſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted that which ſeemed to be a determined period.</p>
               <p>At what time ſoever the Almighty be but pleaſed to ſpeak concerning a Nation, People or Perſon, to pluck up, to pull down or to deſtroy, if
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33556:19"/>that Nation, People or Perſon turn from their evil way, he will Repent of the intended evil, whether Sickneſs or Mortality. The flight of that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row which procured King <hi>Ahabs</hi> Death, was guided by a Divine Hand, who aimed at his Mortal Wounds; yet his raſh going to Battel by the advice of his falſe Prophets, rendred him inſtrumental towards his own Death. The Evangelical Prophet tells us of a Conſumption determined upon the whole Earth, occaſion'd by their great Provocations: The Divine determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation concerning our Lives ſhould not leſſen our care to preſerve our Lives. King <hi>David</hi> underſtood that the determination concerning the Childs Death was paſt, yet he prayed and uſed means to reſtore it. It's a Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Principle, to dream that becauſe the manner and moments of Mens Deaths are appointed, therefore to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33556:20"/>think it Vanity and Cowardice to arm our ſelves, or Antidote our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies againſt the injuries of War and Aſſaults of Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>A Man may live out all Gods time, who wickedly ſhortens his own, and may be permitted to do thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Acts which inevitably tend to his own deſtruction, and cut the Thred of his Dayes.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Murmuring anticipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their Funerals, and Buried them in the Wilderneſs, notwithſtanding their Promiſe of ſeeing <hi>Canaan.</hi> The Impiety of the old World, brought a Deluge, which poſſibly might have been prevented, had their Repentance been as viſible as that of <hi>Ninive,</hi> who were Reprieved from Execution, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Sentence of Death ſeemed Paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon them, their Reformation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented Ruine and Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>The addition of fifteen Years to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33556:20"/>
                  <hi>Hezekias</hi>'s Life, was the reſult of the Divine Favour, but not without ſignal demonſtrations of Repentance. The <hi>Rabins</hi> tell us of one going to gather his Remedies preſcribed by King <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> againſt his peculiar Diſtemper, was met by an Apparition of Death in the ſhape of a Skeleton, which told him with an audible Voice it was too late, for he was ſtruck by the Angel who kept the Key of the Grave. The Moral is obvious enough to a wiſe man, unto whom a word is enough: And I pray Sir excuſe this unravelling my Thoughts in ſuch a ruffled manner from</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Healths Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="letter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:33556:21"/>
               <head>LETTER V.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THeſe Medicines the Doctor hath now Preſcribed, I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed unto you according unto your deſire; the Directions are given with the particular Parcels: and I am of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that a firm belief that men may be many wayes acceſſary towards the ſhortning their own dayes, may much conduce towards the good Succeſs of Remedies, by exciting greater care and circumſpection, and greater Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and Prudence in the management of our ſelves. Sin and Wickedneſs doth apparently ſhorten Life and multiply Diſeaſes. The Life of Man ſeems to be much pared away, but it cannot be artributed unto any Decay in Nature,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33556:21"/>and its univerſal Frame; but rather un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the great Immorality and Impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent extravagancy of Nations and Perſons indulging effeminate, luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and pernicious Cuſtoms. Sin brought Death at firſt; and as Sin in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, ſo Death came nearer by five hundred years. After the Flood men ſinned ſtill, and built Caſtles in the Air, and then Death came nearer by three hundred years: And by <hi>Moſes</hi>'s time a great part of that remnant is pared away, and threeſcore and ten is the period: Had offended Juſtice gone on ſtill to ſhorten mens dayes as men encreaſed in Sin, our Life by this time had not been a Day long; and therefore he no longer deſtroys the Kind, but puniſheth the Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duals, and ſets it down as a ſtanding Rule, That evil ſhal ſlay the Wicked, and he ſhall not live out half his dayes. We cannot now obſerve one
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33556:22"/>in five hundred arrive at that Age unto which they might attain by the courſe of Nature, but end their dayes in Sin and Folly. From ſurfeiting pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds diſſolutions of Members, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxations of Nerves, fractures of Bones, Inflamations of Blood, Crudities of the Stomack, beſides the uncleanly Conſequences of Luſt, which like a Dart ſtrikes through the Liver. Our great Creator hath compoſed our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies like Lamps, and to ſupply the Oyl conſumed by the flame, hath given us Appetites of Hunger and Thirſt, and Reaſon to guide our Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, and the Revelation of his Will to guide our Reaſon; but if men through the depravation of Nature, and the predominancy of Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuffer their Appetites to dethrone their Reaſon, and give way to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance, which extinguiſheth Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Lamp, by corrupting the Oyl,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33556:22"/>or ſpilling it, or blowing out the flame; men may then juſtly expect to be cut off in the midſt of their dayes, and to be made a Sacrifice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their overmuch wickedneſs. I'ts not improbable that <hi>Baalam</hi>'s wiſh to <hi>dye the Death of the Righteous,</hi> did not only include his being ſaved at laſt, but alſo that he might come to his grave in a good old age, with his Fathers in peace, and might not be cut off like the <hi>Moabites</hi> and other Nations, who were to periſh in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs before his eyes. Since Man-kind Bruiſed himſelf with his Fall, he hath corrupted his Blood, and ſowed the Seeds of innumerable Diſeaſes: We daily feel the ſmart of our firſt Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>viz. Thou ſhalt dye the Death;</hi> or, <hi>In Dying thou ſhalt Dye,</hi> or, Thou ſhalt become expoſed unto Sickneſs and Death. Men may naturally be ſaid to <hi>Die daily,</hi> mouldering away by
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33556:23"/>piece-meal. The forbidden Fruit hath produced a Worm that eats our Lives away. The malicious Serpent hath bruiſed our heel, as is obſerved in the <hi>Jeruſalem Targum,</hi> ſuppoſed to be ſaid to the Serpent by Almighty God, viz. <hi>When the Children of the Woman ſhall forſake the Commandments of the Law, thou ſhalt be ſtrong, and ſhalt ſtrike them on the Heel, and inflict Diſeaſes on them.</hi> We are like men going from <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> to <hi>Jericho,</hi> half dead; the Sick and the Aged being but half alive, as ſome Criticks obſerve, <hi>ſenex quaſi ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minex.</hi> With the ſame Motion of our Lungs we draw in Air, we throw away Breath. Some parcels of our ſelves ſteam away continually, and we live a dying Life, or a living Death. Men have ſhortned their dayes by increaſing their Vices. Some men do that by Intemperance which the very Devils deſire to ſhun, <hi>viz.</hi> Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33556:23"/>themſelves before their time: No impious Perſon was ever ſaid in Scripture to be <hi>full of Dayes;</hi> none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full of time, but they that are prepared for Eternity. And we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Read in the Holy Book, of any impenitent perſon that was ever raiſed from the dead, to trye a ſecond time for a Crown: <hi>Lazarus, Tabitha</hi> and the Saints at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> came into the World only to make a Viſit and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare a Glory, and to them it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened literally to have their part in the firſt Reſurrection, upon whom the Second death ſhall have no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>Julian</hi>'s Motto may fit every Man, <hi>An Eagle ſhot through with a Dart fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd with a Quill from its own Wing.</hi> The Life of Man is ſwifter than a Weavers Shuttle, eſpecially if wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs be interwoven, then divine Juſtice cuts the thread; excellently ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Poets Fiction of the three
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33556:24"/>fatal Siſters: The one holding the Diſtaff, the other drawing the Thread, the third cutting it off. Mens Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, like <hi>Hazaels</hi> wet Cloath, prove fatal unto their Lives and Healths, in ſpite of the moſt proper Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. When Sin and Sickneſs is min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled together, no marvel to ſee Mens Bodies moulder, being like the feet of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s Image, made of Clay. It's no wonder to ſee a ſtrange puniſhment to happen unto the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Iniquity. The <hi>Jews</hi> are very often threatned with fore Sickneſſes and wonderful Plagues, if they did not hearken unto the divine Law. That a <hi>wicked</hi> Life procures a <hi>ſhort</hi> one, we find plainly exemplified in moſt of the Bad Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ijam, Athaliah, Ahaziah, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab, Elah, Omri,</hi> and many others; who reigned but two, three or four years apiece; and the reaſons are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33556:24"/>ſometimes recorded, that it was for their ſins which they ſinned, they ſhortned their Lives with their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; in them ſin and a ſudden death reigned together. When mens Luſts have conceived, they bring forth Sin, <hi>and Sin when it is finiſhed, brings forth Death. Pharaoh</hi>'s bloody Perſecution drowned him in the Red Sea. <hi>Ahab</hi>'s cruelty proved fatal to his own Life. The <hi>Samaritan</hi> Lords infidelity preſſed his Soul out of his Body. <hi>Hananiah</hi>'s falſe Propheſie did but predict his own death. <hi>Ahaziah</hi>'s evil Conſultation with the God of <hi>Ekron,</hi> to know whether he ſhould recover of his Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, made his Diſeaſe prove incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. The calumniating rage of the Children againſt the good old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, excited the rage of Bears to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour their Bodies. <hi>Herod</hi>'s vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Oſtentation brought ſuch a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe upon his Body, whereof he had
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33556:25"/>no reaſon to boaſt. <hi>Saphira</hi>'s Perjury ſummoned the feet of thoſe who had carried her Husband to his Grave, to carry her unto the ſame place. <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hadad</hi>'s Curioſity proved the fatal Meſſenger of his death, the Prophet returning Anſwer that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, but ſhould ſurely dye. <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi>'s Idolatry in praying unto falſe gods, provoked the true God to ſtop his breath. <hi>Saul</hi>'s diſobedience unto the King of Kings, brought the King of terrors. <hi>Belſhazzer</hi> for his riotous Revelling, by a Hand-writing on the Wall had the end of his Life and Kingdom denounced againſt him. <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> offering ſtrange Fire, had a ſtranger fire ſent to devour them. The Pride of the Daughters of <hi>Sion</hi> changed their ſweet Smells in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Stink, and their well-ſet Hair into Baldneſs. The Candle of the Wicked is often put out, and the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33556:25"/>Number of his Months cut off in the Middle. But, Sir, that no Cloud may have power to diſcompoſe the Serenity of your dayes, but that you may enjoy a Spring of Happineſs in the Winter of Age, and may want nothing but Want it ſelf, ſhall never be left out of the Prayers and Wiſhes of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your true Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER VI.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received your dated the ſixth inſtant, wherein you ſeem to wonder, that the Cauſe of your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is not long ſince removed, and you reſtored unto a ſtate of health. I beſeech you give me leave to deal
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33556:26"/>plainly, and to tell you that there are Moral as well as Natural Cauſes of diſeaſes; and unleſs both be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, Remedies very often prove ineffectual: And the ſincere belief of this conduceh very much towards the ſucceſs of Medicines. Many of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> were ſick and weak, and loſt their Lives, for their unworthy reception of the Holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. If men contemn the Sacred Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Son of God, how can they expect the Almighty goodneſs ſhould take care of their bodies? and if they neglect to commemorate his Death, they have little reaſon to expect he ſhould regard their Lives, although precious in his ſight is the Death of his Saints. <hi>Miriam</hi>'s Sedition raiſed a tumultous diſturbance in the harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of her health: The diſſimulation of <hi>Gehaza</hi>'s Tongue procured the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie upon his Skin: <hi>Uzziah</hi>'s invade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33556:26"/>the Prieſts office, and Burning Incenſe, cauſed the divine diſpleaſure to ſmoke againſt him. <hi>Abimelech</hi> was reſtored to his health, when he reſtored <hi>Abrahams</hi> Wife, but not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: When our bleſſed Saviour cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the man ſick of a Palſie, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave him his ſins, to ſhew him they were the cauſe of his ſickneſs. We may obſerve in our Saviours dayes, that Infidelity did as it were tye up the hands of Omnipotence, and ſet bounds to the operation of his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Works on mens bodies. St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelm</hi> obſerves, that the reaſon why diſeaſes did ſo much abound in his time, was, becauſe the holy Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt was irreverently received at <hi>Eaſter. Jezabel</hi> for her Impenitence is threatned to be caſt into a bed, and her Children to be killed with Death: Good men may dye, but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be killed with Death: The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33556:27"/>are frequently Menaced with Death and Sickneſs, that ſhall preſume to ſpeak without a Miſſion from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. In vain are external Remedies applyed, when the Cauſe is internal: The Fable of the Kite when ſick, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring help and recovery, but being denyed by reaſon of her rapine and violence; it affords an excellent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. The ſickneſs of the Body is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times deſigned to promote the Health of the Soul; and the Leproſie on <hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Fleſh may conduce towards the whitening of his Mind: They are ſent as tryals of Grace, and are Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of Divine mercy. When the Queſtion was asked our Saviour, <hi>Who ſinned, this Man or his Parents, that be was born Blind?</hi> Our Lord Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Neither this Man nor his Parents;</hi> but it was for the Declaration of Divine Mercy, that the work of God might be made manifeſt in his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33556:27"/>Cure and Recovery: Alſo the ſickneſs of <hi>Lazarus</hi> was deſigned for the Glory of God, and Honour of our Saviour, that he might have an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to manifeſt his Divine Power. <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> adviſeth Phyſitians, to ſearch if there be not ſomething Divine in the Cauſes of Diſeaſes. The Living man ſeldom complains with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving his maker a cauſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict puniſhment; for the righteous Judge doth not afflict willingly nor grieve the Children of Men: There is ſome Babiloniſh Garment hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected the Body with Leproſie, or ſome ſpiritual diſeaſe in the mind, that hath procured the thorn in the fleſh, when the Rod of God utters it's voice, and men are fed with the Bread of Affliction and with the Water of Adverſity, in order to cure the tympany of Pride, the Feavour of Paſſion, the Dropſie of Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33556:28"/>The plague in the Body is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſent to cure the Plague in the Heart: Sin is that root of bitterneſs from whence all our troubles in the fleſh ſpring up. Men are like <hi>Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam,</hi> when any thing pains or hurts their Bodies, are apt to Blame and ſtrike the External Inſtrument, but never mind the Angel that ſtands in the way with a drawn Sword, and cauſed that inſtrument to hurt. There are many happy intentions Divine goodneſs aims at in laying diſeaſes on mens bodies: Sometimes the ſacrificing Knife is laid upon the neck of an <hi>Iſaac,</hi> to try whether the indulgent Parent will prefer the life of his natural Son before the Will of his heavenly Father. When men come to perceive that there is no ſoundneſs in their fleſh, nor reſt in their bones, becauſe of their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and that it was their own
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33556:28"/>wickedneſs that corrected them, and procured the Plagues, the Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Inflamations and extream burnings, that attended as Pages up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their pride, wantonneſs, intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and carnality; and this produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth a ſtrict commune with their hearts upon their ſick beds, ſo that they make a Diligent ſearch into the cauſes of their Diſtempers; then they find a rebuke given unto the diſeaſe. Sir, I pray excuſe this great freedom, from one who I hope ſhall not ſtand in need of many words to perſwade you, that he is</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your inviolably affectionate Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="letter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:33556:29"/>
               <head>LETTER VII.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AMongſt the many things which conduce towards the rendring the uſe of Remedies effectual, I think nothing can contribute more than our endeavour to uſe thoſe Means which may be influential towards the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing the divine Bleſſing: And amongſt many others, I judge theſe that follow are very conſiderable: To begin with a ſerious Repentance for our former Miſcarriages, which often proves very ſucceſſeful towards Health and Recovery. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Repentance proved a Soveraign Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter againſt the Stings of the fiery Serpents: And King <hi>Davids</hi> Remorſe prevailed with the deſtroying Angel to ſheathe his Sword, after the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33556:29"/>of Seventy thouſand People. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboams</hi> Repentance at the preaching of <hi>Shemaiah,</hi> prevented the deſtruction of himſelf and his Princes. When mens fleſh is conſumed, and they are afflicted with ſtrong pains upon their Beds, then the Almighty looks upon Men, to ſee if any ſay they have ſinned and perverted that which is right, to deliver them from going down to the pit, that their Lives may ſee the light. When the Divine hand binds men with Fetters, and holds them in the Cords of Affliction, then he ſhews them their work and their tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they have exceeded: <hi>Then he opens their Ears to Diſcipline, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands that they return from Iniquity;</hi> If they obey and ſerve him, <hi>they ſhall ſpend their Dayes in Proſperity, and their Years in Pleaſure:</hi> But if they obey not, <hi>they ſhall Dye in their Youth, for God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth not the Life of the wicked,</hi> as <hi>Elihu</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:33556:30"/>tells <hi>Job:</hi> The ſick Bed is the attiring room of the Grave, in which Men ſhould be preparing themſelves for the Solemnities of their Funerals: by lingering Diſtempers men are gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally putting off their Vail of Fleſh, <hi>to be Cloathed upon with their houſe which is from Heaven.</hi> When Sickneſs hath done its Errand, and accompliſhed the end for which it was ſent, then it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives a Commiſſion to depart; its that which leads Men by the Hand unto their long homes, and gives them a Proſpect of that Houſe appointed for all Living: Diſeaſes are ſent to unravel humane Nature, but when the inward Man is renewed by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes of the outward, and men hold faſt their Integrity, notwithſtanding the Almighty toucheth their Bone and their Fleſh, and bodily Pain give a proſpect of endleſs Pleaſure, then the Diſeaſe many times takes its leave.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33556:30"/>When Sickneſs makes Men ſenſible of the Vanity of Beauty and Strength, which a blaſt of Wind, or a lump of Phlegme may take from them, when it makes Men liſten unto the Striking of the Clock of Time with greater Attention, and excites their endeavours to render Death a ſtingleſs Serpent, then the great part of the Cure is perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: when Men are as 'twere knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the gates of the Grave by Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Agonies of Body, and the blow of Gods heavy Hand preſſeth Men ſore, ſo that a Man may read the Sentence of ſome Mens Deaths written in their Foreheads, in the lines of a lingering Diſeaſe, the difficult mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Lungs to draw in Air, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like a Paſſing-Bell alwayes ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Ears, yet upon their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Repentance many times comes a Reprieve. When the Arrows of the Almighty, <hi>viz.</hi> Diſeaſes, fly thick in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33556:31"/>the world, and are ſhot ſometimes into Mens Lungs, and ſometimes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Joynts and Hearts, and give denomination unto various Diſeaſes; there they will ſtick untill pulled out by an Omnipotent Hand, a firm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of whoſe Divine Power, doth mightily conduce towards the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Bleſſing of Heaven with the uſe of Remedies. The Power of our Bleſſed Lord is the ſame now in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as when on Earth, his Hand from Heaven can reach all our Maladies, and cure, like the Weapon Salve, at a diſtance; if Men did but act a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Faith and a holy Confidence in the Divine Providence, and as it were touch the Hem of their Saviours Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they would quickly find a heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Virtue go forth towards their Cure. When Men are diſquieted by Pains, and caſt down by Sickneſs, their only way to Recovery, is to hope in him
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33556:31"/>who is the Health of their Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and in quietneſs and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence they will find Strength. To hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelves under the mighty Hand of God, is the way to be exalted to Health in his due time. Acts of Faith are engaging, and the way to obtain the Divine Power, is to glorifie it in our dependance. When Miracles were in their full force, the effect is alwaies aſcribed unto Faith; our Saviour told the Woman her Faith had made her whole. Again, humbly to implore the help of that great Phyſician who was Typified by the Brazen Serpent, would be a very effectual means to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red both of the Sting and Pain of Sickneſs: It well becomes the moſt holy Soul under Diſtempers, to abound with an <hi>O Spare me, that I may recover Strength.</hi> When Men are like <hi>Moſes,</hi> commanded to go up into a Mount,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33556:32"/>as it were, of a Sick-Bed, and Dye there, the ſame Hand that Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed muſt make whole: many loſe their Lives for want of asking it at his Hands, who grants it if Invited to our Bed-ſides by fervent Prayers, joyned with Faith and Patience. When the only wiſe God reſolves to make Men ſick with ſmiting them, they ought to beware of Murmuring and Impatience, which doth exaſperate all Calamities; it being far more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous towards recovery, patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to hope and quietly to wait for the Salvation of God; for they that wait upon the Lord have a Promiſe they ſhall renew their Strength, and be ſaved with a temporal as well as a ſpiritual Salvation, if they continue in Faith and Patience with Sobriety. The Poets have an excellent Fiction, that the Image of the Goddeſs <hi>Augerine</hi> was
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33556:32"/>with a Muffler at her Mouth, placed at the Temple of <hi>Volupia;</hi> ſignifying that Pleaſure ſhould be their Portion who bear Sickneſſes with Patience, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Submiſſion.</p>
               <p>Good Men never queſtion the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Favour ſo much at any time as under ſickneſs; becauſe the Body diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſeth the Mind, and hinders the free exerciſe of ſpiritual Reaſon: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, they have not ſuch expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from their Saviours Sufferings; for we never read he was ever Sick, yet he had Paſſions equivalent to Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as Hunger, Thirſt, Wearineſs, which afflicted his Body with Pain, and therefore can be toucht with the feeling of our Infirmities: The beſt way to obtain Cure, is by the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of a Divine Faith to ſhake off Diſeaſes as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did the Viper from his Hand. And Sir, that the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33556:33"/>great Phyſician may make your Soul like his Body in the Goſpel, every whit whole, ſhall be the Deſire of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your true Friend and faithful Servant, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER VIII.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours dated the Second of this Month, wherein you acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge your ſelf a Convert unto the ſeveral Arguments of Diſcourſe which have formerly paſſed between us; but you ſeem very much to doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther humane Prudence, Care and Art can any way contribute unto long Life: And that they may be very ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33556:33"/>thereunto, there is nothing more plain and evident. Certainly King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s departing from <hi>Keylak</hi> diverted <hi>Sauls</hi> Rage, and preſerved his own Life for that time: And our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours own practice in preſerving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf until the time he knew that his hour was come, is recorded for our Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Mariners ſaved their Lives by abiding in the Ship, who otherwiſe in all probability might have been Drowned: The Wiſdom of <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> in obſerving the Angels advice, and flying into <hi>Egypt</hi> with the bleſſed Babe, in all humane probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it prevented his Death at <hi>Bethlehem.</hi> The Centurion Importun'd our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to cure his Servant, which he would never have done, if it had not conduced towards the prolongation of his Life. 'Twas not without cauſe that <hi>Naomi</hi> was foretold <hi>Obed</hi> ſhould be a reſtorer of her Age. As fire dies for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33556:34"/>want of air, and is extinguiſhed when the flame is ſuffocated; ſo doth our vital flame: as our Spirits are repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Air, ſo are our ſanguine Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours by Aliments. Much may be done by Art for the retarding the courſe of Nature, as may be ſeen in many Inſects and Animals, and in Men reſtored from Conſumptive pine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sickneſſes, their fleſh becoming like that of Children, as in <hi>Naamans</hi> Caſe: The efficacy of Remedies with ſome is ſo great, that their Youth is as 'twere renewed like the Eagle, their natural ſtrength not abating at a great Age: Moreover, it doth not ſeem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that means ſhould be uſed with good ſucceſs to anſwer all other inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Nature, and be uſed in vain in attaining that which is the moſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thing in Nature, and which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders a Man capable of perfection in all Arts and Sciences, <hi>viz.</hi> Health. And
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33556:34"/>yet as none can ſpeak of Death by experience, becauſe they who ſpeak of it have not felt it, and they who have felt it cannot ſpeak of it; the Caſe is much the ſame concerning Life: For unleſs a Man live unto ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream old Age, he will not believe his Life hath been prolonged, but rather that his hour was not yet come: but yet it's not inconſiſtent with reaſon to ſay, that he who would Infallibly have Dyed of a Gangreen in his Leg, hath had his Life prolonged, when his Leg was Cured; or to ſay, that a Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Body hath been ſaved from Death, when reſtored to a healthful State by a Medicinal Diet, which hath added Oyl to the Lamp of Life. The <hi>Nectar</hi> and <hi>Ambroſia</hi> of the Poets, which kept their gods from growing old, ſeems to be an Emblem of the Tree of Life, which was to have been a Reſtorer of Nature, as well as a Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33556:35"/>of future things. Suppoſe we with <hi>Pithagoras,</hi> that Life is a ſtrait line, and that the accidents which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb it, and at length bring Death, conſtitute another Line; and as theſe two lines incline leſs or more one towards another, Death approaches ſooner or later, and conſequently Life is longer or ſhorter; yet may we not ſuppoſe that Divine Providence and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Prudence may probably conduce towards the retarding the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of thoſe lines? Or ſuppoſe with the <hi>Ariſtotelians,</hi> that Life conſiſts in the union of Heat and Moiſture, and Death approacheth by the Predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the contrary Qualities, <hi>viz.</hi> Cold and Dryneſs; why may not ſuch means as preſerves the former, and keeps back the latter, have a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural tendency to prolong Life? Or ſuppoſe with the <hi>Chymiſts,</hi> that Life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in a volatile Armoniack Salt, why
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33556:35"/>may we not ſuppoſe that Art impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, may compoſe ſuch fixed Alkali, as may ſtop the wingy motions of the former Volatility?</p>
               <p>The pleaſing gratifications of Senſe walk Hand in Hand with Death, and purſueth Mortals as the Waves of the univerſal Deluge did the Poſterity of <hi>Cain;</hi> and though they went from one ſtory to another, higher and higher, yet at laſt they were overflowed. Though Temperance doth not alwayes prove an Antidote againſt Sickneſs, yet it's a likely means. Sir, I pray diſtribute my Service where you think it's due, for it is time to come to a full point, and to tell you that in Truth I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours in all that Power and Will can manifeſt, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="letter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:33556:36"/>
               <head>LETTER IX.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours dated the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, wherein you give me an account of the great Sickneſs and Mortality of your Town and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, now Languiſhing under this Epidemick Feaver, which indeed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in the City alſo, and carrieth hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, if not thouſands unto their long Homes. You may eaſily believe that there are greater Languors, Sickneſſes, Weakneſſes and decayes of Nature now than in former Ages; (though thanks be to God, Peſtilences have not been very fatal of late years) and we obſerve from our weekly Bills of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, that the numbers of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed are greatly augmented; for in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33556:36"/>the year 1604. there dyed 4323, and 895 of the Plague: but in the year 1659. there dyed 14720, and 36 of the Plague; and yet we obſerve near the ſame number of perſons Born and Chriſtned both years; ſo that the Diſproportion is near nine Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in a year in about ſixty years diſtance. We may obſerve in the ſpace of ſixty years, ſo ſmall a ſpot of ground as a Church-yard ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes up a whole Pariſh. I knew an old Sexton in <hi>London,</hi> who told me he lived to Bury his Pariſh al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt three times over. As one Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration comes on the Stage, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goeth off: And very evident it is, that more dye now in a ſtate of Childhood than in former Ages. We lick new bodies off our Trenchers once in ſeven years; and the very fear of a Clymacterical Year hath Killed ſome, who have not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33556:37"/>how groundleſs ſuch a fear is. In the dayes of Ancient times it was a ſtrange thing to hear of the death of a young Child, according unto the ordinary courſe of Nature. Some of the Jewiſh Doctors tell us, that there was not a Son dyed of a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral death before his Father for near three thouſand years after the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but the courſe of Nature was obſerved, and he that was born firſt, dyed firſt; untill <hi>Terah</hi>'s time, who was the firſt that taught the People to make Images of Clay, and to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Divine Worſhip with Idolatry; and as a puniſhment of his Sin, his ſon <hi>Haran</hi> was ſnatcht away before him; and <hi>Moſes</hi> obſerves, that <hi>Haran</hi> dyed before his Father <hi>Terah,</hi> in the Land of his Nativity: And we find it was looked upon as a great Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Male Heir of <hi>Eli</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily as ſoon as born dyed for many
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33556:37"/>Generations; ſo that an Old man could not be ſeen of his Poſterity. And we find the good Woman ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulating paſſionately with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, when ſhe ſaith, <hi>Art thou come to call my Sins to remembrance, and to ſlay my Son?</hi> Every Age hath its pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar diſeaſes: In the ſtate of Infancy Life is like a Spark in a pile of Wood; the Candle is ſo newly lighted, that every breath of Air, or the leaſt ſhaking puts it out, and it dyes. Childhood is ſo active and unwary, ſo ſubject to run into dangers, that unleſs a Meſſenger be ſent from Heaven, to ſtand Sentinel and watch its playing, ſleeping, eating and drinking, it's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to death every minute. The Middle age is apter to lend its help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hand to the uſe of Remedies, but when we conſider how many new diſtempers invade us, and how many old ones intermingled with collateral
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33556:38"/>complications, and many Diſeaſes are not fully underſtood as in time they may be; and many Symptoms are often alike, and ſometimes there are none at all, as in ſeveral Impoſtumes; and ſome Diſeaſes are lodged in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote parts of the Body, that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times no application can be made, or at leaſt the effects of Medicines can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach them untill after two or three Alterations and Concoctions, which change the Species of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines: And ſometimes new Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods come upon the Stage, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter old Foundations. Old Age hath Diſeaſes incurable by nature. The Houſe muſt fall when the Foundation is decayed. Old men in Scripture ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count are ſaid to be <hi>as good as dead,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> was. In ſome Diſeaſes the Patient ſeems Bailable, yet a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper lyeth in ambuſh, and ſets upon him with full ſtrength, when
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33556:38"/>the bitterneſs of death ſeemed to be paſt: and ſome men live and dye like Fools, pour in Drink and let out Life, and ſo by inconſideration pull the Monumental Stone upon their own heads. Men are like Water, if the Sluces be opened it runs away apace, if the Current be ſtopt it ſwells and grows troubleſome, and ſpills over; if it ſtands ſtill, then it ſtinks and putrifies. Some Sickneſſes walk in darkneſs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Angels are wrapt up in the Curtains of Immateriality, whom we cannot ſee but feel: in ſome Chronick diſtempers men walk about, and hear Paſſing-bells ring for ſtronger men. There is no age of Man but hath ſome Poſterns and Out-lets to death, out of which thouſands paſs into the Land of Forgetfulneſs: Every breath of wind troubles our Faces, and our little Cares wrinkle our Foreheads, and trifling accidents dig our Graves.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33556:39"/>In Feavors men ride poſt to the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of death, they prove a Beeſome of Deſtruction to three parts of <hi>Adam</hi>'s race. If all the ages of all Mankind were put together, it would ſcarce make One and twenty to each ſingle perſon. It's more natural for Youth to dye than the Aged, it being more common, having more natural cauſes, as being more ſubject to acute Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which ſurprize men ſuddenly and undiſcernably; but to dye of Age, is a very rare Thing; old Age is a young Death. But to ſpeak ſtrictly, all men dye before they come to be of age, every man being within an inch of Death. Like a Mariner at Sea, we carry our Lives in our hands. Many a man in a ſtate of health hath a ſecret Enemy lying hid, ready to ſurprize: Either Gods Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers cleave our Reins in ſunder with the Stone or Strangury, or our feet
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33556:39"/>are ſet in the Stocks by the Gout; or our Breath is corrupt by the Pty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, or our Gaul is poured on the ground by the Diſſentery, or our Skin cleaves to our Bones by a Hectick. The Clock hath ſtruch Twelve this night, therefore take it not ill that I abruptly ſtyle my ſelf</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours whileſt I am <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER X.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours Dated the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, wherein you ſpeak very ſlightly of old Age, as if you did not look upon it as ſo great a bleſſing; and alſo ſeem to Queſtion whether the Patriarchs lived ſo long as ſome imagine. To which I anſwer, you
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33556:40"/>are certainly under a great miſtake: for nothing is more certain than that the Antediluvian Patriarchs were very long lived; and particularly Father <hi>Adam,</hi> who may well be accounted above a thouſand years old, if we compute that time whch he might have lived had he been born as <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſalem</hi> was; we may judge him at his Creation as Perfect as one of the Ancients at two hundred: They out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived all their titles of Conſanguini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and yet none of them lived a compleat Thouſand years; which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly might be to accompliſh the threatning unto <hi>Adam,</hi> That the day he eat the <hi>forbidden Fruit</hi> he ſhould <hi>Dye;</hi> computing a day for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years: But a more probable reaſon may be, to Demonſtrate to Man the Vanity of Life, when thoſe who lived longeſt, could not arrive to that Period, which compared to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33556:40"/>Gods Eternity, is but a day. As there are at this day ſome who exceed a hundred, ſo there are a hundred times as many who do not arrive at that Period. Had men in all Ages and Places arrived at the age of the Patriarchs, the Earth by this time had not been able to ſuſtain the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants with Food. The <hi>Egyptians</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated the bounds of mens dayes from the weight of their Hearts; and judged a hundred years the utmoſt period, taking their eſtimate from the weight of their Hearts, which they ſay increaſeth two Drachms every year under fifty, and then decreaſeth two Drachms untill a hundred: But this opinion ſeems queſtionable. The reaſon given by the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> for Contracting the year of Jubilee from one hundred to fifty, and from fifty to five and twenty, is grounded upon the Suppoſition that the age
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33556:41"/>of man is contracted. To what cauſes to conſign the long Lives of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, it need not be Difficult, if we conſider how neceſſary it was ſo to be, for the propagation of Mankind, and peopling the World with Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants; and alſo for the learning Arts and Sciences, wherein it was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Men ſhould have the experience of former Ages: For as many Senſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions breed an Experiment, ſo many Experiments breed a Science. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral motions of the Heavenly Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies could not be known, without a long time to obſerve their Motions and Revolutions. It was an old com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, that Art was long, and Life was ſhort, and therefore Almighty God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned mens lives accordingly. We now account him wondrous Old who lives fourſcore Summers, to ſee the Reſurrection of the Year fourſcore times. The length of mens age ſince
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33556:41"/>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> dwelt amongſt us, ſeems con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably abbreviated, he computing Threeſcore and ten the ordinary pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod unto which men generally arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in thoſe times: Whereas now a third part of all that are born in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Cities dye under ſeven years old; and the greateſt part of thoſe that are alive, are between fifteen and five and thirty. Few Princes, either <hi>Jewiſh, German, Greek</hi> or <hi>Roman,</hi> arrived at Fourſcore. Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> outlived all her Predeceſſors ſince the Conqueſt: And I think his Majeſty our preſent Sovereign (whom God grant long to live) is the eldeſt Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Head in <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> And it's to me obſervable, that during the ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the firſt Temple there were but eighteen High-prieſts, but three hundred while the ſecond ſtood; and but ten years difference between the ſtanding of the former and the latter.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33556:42"/>Which plainly demonſtrates, that mens Lives have been cut and pared away in ſeveral Ages. The Fathers in the primitive times had great Advantages for the Prolongation of their Lives, as they had conveyed to them the Nature of Life-preſerving Remedies from <hi>Adam,</hi> who gave Names to all Creatures according to their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Qualities: And wonderful was their skill in all the Secrets of Nature. Alſo the Air in the firſt Ages of the World might be more pure, and not corrupted with terrene Exhalations, as it was after the Flood had drencht it; and for ought we know, its Fruits might be more Nutritive. Moreover, <hi>Adam</hi> was the immediate Work of God, and being come as it were new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Shop of his Creator, he could not be like a Houſe built of rotten Timber, but of a far ſtronger Conſtitution than this weak Age af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33556:42"/>Their Bodies were not waſted with fucceſſion of Sickneſſes, nor wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken'd with hereditary Diſeaſes, but were armed to reſiſt thoſe few things contrary to their healths. The ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalities of Diſeaſes were not ſo preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantly conveyed from Parent to Child, their Infants were not ſo tenderly brought up; waſtfull Ryot was a ſtranger to them, and variety of Meats was to them unknown: their Nature was not oppreſt with burthens, and forced to ſtagger with her load. We cannot with any ſhew of Reaſon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to miſtake in the manner of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting the years of the Patriarchs; for if you ſuppoſe them to be only Lunar years, and that twelve of theirs made but one of ours, then groſs ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities muſt follow from thence; as that they were Prolifique at ſeven years of age, <hi>Enoch</hi> being no more when he begat <hi>Methuſalem:</hi> At that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33556:43"/>rate the Date of their Lives muſt be reckoned ſhorter than many of ours. Moreover, the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>Abraham</hi> dyed <hi>in a good Old Age,</hi> and <hi>full of Dayes,</hi> being one hundred ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty and five years old; which Number, according to that computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was but ſeventeen years and a half; a very ridiculous old Age. But it is very manifeſt that <hi>Moſes</hi>'s compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the year was the ſame with ours; for mention is made of the firſt, ſecond and ſeventh Month, and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is alſo made of the ſeventeenth day of the Month. We find but one Womans Age recorded in Scripture, and that is <hi>Sarah:</hi> Some give this reaſon, Becauſe a Woman firſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned the Shortning the Lives of men, by liſtning to the Serpent. Old Age is doubtleſs a very great Bleſſing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubſervient to great and noble ends, namely, our better Preparation
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33556:43"/>for a bleſſed Eternity: And there are ſome Priviledges that holy Souls are capable of in this World, which they cannot partake of in the Regions of immortal Bliſs, and they are the Opportunities of Doing good to others, and preparing them for the Eternal Manſions, and thereby Brightning their own Diadems, and making their weight of Glory the Heavier by turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many to Righteouſneſs. Which that you may doe, is the Wiſh of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Cordial Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER XI.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours dated the Second Inſtant, wherein you ſeem to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether the Practice of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33556:44"/>on have any tendency towards Health and long life; becauſe ſometimes good Men Dye ſuddain and Immature Deaths: But nothing is more plain and evident, than that the Carkaſſes of good <hi>Iſraelites</hi> may fall in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of this World, whoſe Souls may be entertained in the Heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi> A good Prophet, for ſome ſingle Act of Diſobedience, may be made a Prey to a devouring Lyon: If an <hi>Eli</hi> neglect to Chaſten his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Children, he may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to break his Neck: When <hi>Uzzth</hi> ſhall touch the Ark without a Commiſſion, his Death ſhall imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſucceed his Raſhneſs: When a <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhall neglect to Circumcize his Child, an Angel ſhall threaten his Life with a drawn Sword: When a <hi>Jonas</hi> ſhall go contrary to a Divine Command, he ſhall be in danger of being ſwallowed up by Death, as
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33556:44"/>well as by a Whale. Many times Judgment begins at the Houſe of God, and he makes good Men the examples of his Severity in this Life: It's thought that King <hi>David</hi>'s numbering the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, was the laſt Act he did, before he took his Bed. Evil Angels ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times contend with good ones, about the Bodies of good Men: <hi>Sampſon</hi> loſt his natural Strength by his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience and violation of his Vow, rather than by the meer Cutting off his Hair, it being rather a Moral than a Natural Cauſe of his Weakneſs: The Righteous may ſometimes be taken away from the evil to come, as the good Patriarchs were before the Flood; and as <hi>Abijah</hi> was laid to ſleep before the Calamity of his Fathers Houſe: And ſometimes the Child may derive thoſe Diſtempered Humours from the Parent, which may prove
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33556:45"/>the occaſion of its Death. Though God hath Promiſed long Life to them that Obey, yet he hath never Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that he would not ſometimes as it were borrow Mens natural Lives, and make a happy exchange, make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good his Promiſe, and anſwering other ends of his Providence, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compencing the loſs of a Temporal with the grant of Eternal Life. On the conrrary, becauſe ſometimes wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Men live long, to infer Piety hath no Influence on Mens Health and Longaevity, is as great a Miſtake; for a long and a wicked Life may be twiſted together for Reaſons beſt known to Omnipotence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as the Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Cain</hi> may be longer Liv'd than any of the Patriarchs, being reſerved to be puniſht in the general Deluge; and <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> Reigned longer than any of the Kings of <hi>Judah.</hi> But no
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33556:45"/>more of this at preſent, only I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you take me as I am, and ever muſt be</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your real Friend and Servant, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER XII.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received Yours, wherein you Write very contemptuouſly of the Art of Phyſick, as if the uſe of Medicine were not an Ordinance of God, and men were not oblig'd in Conſcience to the application of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies: But with your leave, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more plain and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than that Phyſick is a Divine Inſtitution. He who breathed into man the breath of Life, and by an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Law hath commanded him not
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33556:46"/>to Kill, but commanded him to Pray for his daily Bread, with all the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſupports of this Life, hath thereby laid an Obligation upon him, to uſe all means to preſerve both his own and others Lives: Many of the Inſpired Pen-men were well Skill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Medicine, particularly St. <hi>Luke,</hi> who was the Evangelical Amanuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, and Wrote a Hiſtory of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviours Paſſion and Life, he was called the beloved Phyſician: and we find the great Doctor of the Gentiles preſcribe Wine as a chearing Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al unto his <hi>Timothy,</hi> under his frequent Infirmities for his Healths ſake: nay, the Bleſſed God is pleaſed to Style himſelf the Lord, the Phyſitian; and the Holy Jeſus derives his Name from his healing Nature, and tells us, though the Whole need no Phyſitian, yet the Sick do: and the Holy Ghoſt aſſures us by the Pſalmiſts Pencil, that God hath
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33556:46"/>given Medicines to heal Mens Sickneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Every man is bound by the Law of God and Nature to endeavour to keep his clayey Tenement in reparation, and if he neglect it and let it run to ruine, he may be in danger of being Indicted at the Bar of Heaven for Dilapidations. The holy Prophet reſſecting upon the deplorable Condition of the Church, with <hi>The whole Head ſick and the whole Heart faint,</hi> full of Wounds, Bruiſes and Putrefactions, being not <hi>Bound up nor mollified with Oyntments;</hi> plainly intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, how neceſſary he thought the natural as well as the ſpiritual Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of fit Remedies; lamening there was no Balm in <hi>Gilead,</hi> nor any Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian there. <hi>Jothams</hi> Parable may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the World, that not only the Olive, the Figg-tree and the Vine are uſefull to chear the Heart of God and man, but alſo the Bramble hath a healing Vertue in ſome Diſtempers.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33556:47"/>Since the appearance of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> we may eat of every Tree in the Garden, asking no Queſtion for Conſcience ſake, for <hi>the Earth is the Lords and the fulneſs thereof:</hi> The wonderful work of Providence is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry apparent in preſerving the Seminal Vertue of Plants in the Deluge, when we read not of any Seed ſecured in the Ark; the Innocent Dove ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Leaf to the new World, Preacht a Sermon of Divine goodneſs. The Utility of Phyſical Remedies, is not only demonſtrated by Chriſtians, but alſo by Jews and Pagans: In the Temple of <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> there was a Fountain of Oyl, with a Golden Arch, a perfect Symbol of Phyſick, deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting its uſefulneſs and Honour. The deſign of Medicine is not to prevent Death, but to render Life comfortable, and to preſerve Natures Lamp burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, until there's no more Oyl to feed
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33556:47"/>it. The Son of <hi>Syrack</hi> Counſels men to Honour the Phyſitian with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour due unto him; telling us, that God had created him, and hath given Men Skill that he might be Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his marvellous works, with the Medicines that he hath Created out of the Earth, to heal Men and take away their pains. <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Aeſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapius</hi> amongſt the Greeks were ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as gods for the excellency of their Invention in Phyſick; and the knotty Staff, the Serpent, the Pine-Apple, the Dragon, the Dog, and the Cock, with which the pourtraicture of <hi>Aeſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapius</hi> was Beautified, were very ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant Symbols. Medicine hath by barbarous Nations been account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sacred: The Prieſts of <hi>Memphis</hi> were bound to Write in the Temple of <hi>Iſis</hi> ſuch Remedies as were found effectual: the ſame practice the Greeks practiſed at the Temple of <hi>Apollo;</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:33556:48"/>Authorizing Medicine by Religion, and Converting Remedies into Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: The <hi>Jews</hi> tell us, that at the Temple of <hi>Solomon,</hi> there hung a long Catalogue of the Vertues of all Plants, collected by <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf; ſo that if any were Smitten with any Diſeaſe, he might go and gather his Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: And the Holy Prophets in their Deſcriptions of the Holy Land, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the excellency thereof from its abounding with Trees, whoſe Leaves are good for Medicine. St. <hi>James</hi> placeth our Viſiting the Sick, amongſt the parts of that pure Religion which is undefiled before God; and our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour numbers this Chriſtian Duty amongſt thoſe good works, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto which we ſhall receive our final Sentence; when he ſaith, <hi>I was ſick and ye Viſited me:</hi> As the <hi>Jews</hi> by their particular Laws were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to be at the Charge of Cure
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33556:48"/>unto any whom they had hurt or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured in their Health, much more ought men to be concerned for their own Health and Recovery when Sick and Weak. King <hi>Aſa</hi> was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended for adviſing with, but for truſting to the Phyſitians, making them his end, when they were only the means; which was Recorded to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us, that we ſhould uſe means as if there were no Providence, and yet truſt Providence as if there were no Means. When the Mariners in the Ship in which St. <hi>Paul</hi> Sailed, were in danger of Drowning, he told them they could not be ſafe unleſs they did abide in the Ship, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Safety of their Lives was promiſed him. When the Lives of the <hi>Jews</hi> were in danger, Queen <hi>Eſther</hi> not only appointed a Faſt to Implore the Protection of Heaven, but alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared a Feaſt, the better to prevail
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33556:49"/>with the King. The Prophet <hi>David</hi> not only Truſted in the Name of the Lord, when he went againſt <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah,</hi> but alſo uſed his Stone and Sling: So <hi>Jacob</hi> ſent a Preſent to pacifie the Anger of his Brother, as well as made Supplication to the great Peace-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. The Bodies of good Men, are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, and neglecting the ſame, is reputed a part of Will-worſhip, and ſtrictly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited. <hi>Baalam</hi>'s Aſs may Inſtruct the World that a merciful Man ought to be merciful to his Beaſt; how much rather ought he like the <hi>Shunamite</hi> Woman, take a Journey if the Caſe require it, for the recovery of a Child from the Jaws of Death? <hi>The Life is more worth than Meat, and the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy than Raiment.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> thought their Lives more worth than their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, for they told the King, If they had been Sold for <hi>Bond-men,</hi> they
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33556:49"/>had held their Peace. Life is the form of Gods own Oath. Thoſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which are the Members of Chriſt, ought to have Care and Reſpect uſed towards them, that they may be fit for the Service of the Soul. That which was ſick was not to be Offer'd in Sacrifice under the Law, and they that are ſick, are not fit to Offer Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices: The Father of Lyes never ſpake a greater Truth, than when he ſaid, <hi>Skin for Skin, and all that a Man hath, will he give for his Life.</hi> It's a grand Impiety, under a pretence of Gods Power, to be Diſobedient to his Will, in neglecting the means of Health; that's to try what he can do, and yet to neglect what he Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, in not adminiſtring thoſe things which are requiſite and neceſſary for the Body. King <hi>Solomon,</hi> who had a Patent granted him from the King of Heaven, to receive the greateſt
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33556:50"/>meaſure of Wiſdom of any Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after him, made it his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſearch into the Nature of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables, from the talleſt Cedar, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hyſſop that grows out of the Wall; and though his Gold was ſo plentiful as to pave his Palace, and he had all the Delights of the Sons of Men, yet he Condeſcended unto the Study and Improvement of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and tells us, That there is a time to heal; every Herb bearing Seed, being preſcribed for Food or Phyſick by our great Creator. It's not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable but that the Sons of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets had a Phyſical Intention in ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the Herbs for their Pottage, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were miſtaken in the particular Plant, and gathered a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, inſtead of a wholſome one: <hi>Ahab</hi> underſtood the uſefulneſs of a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Herbs, when he coveted <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi>'s Vineyard to Convert it into the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33556:50"/>ſame. The good Will of him that dwelt in the Buſh, is further decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto Mankind by the Vertue that he hath planted in the Leaves, and Fruit that grow thereon, being uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the healing of the Nations in a Natural as well as in a Myſtical Sence. Thoſe perſons who cut up Mallows by the Roots in Holy <hi>Job</hi>'s time, could not but underſtand their Phyſical Vertue: A Dinner of Herbs with Evangelical Charity, is preferr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Solomon,</hi> before a Coſtly Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet; and thoſe Medicinal Herbs of Mint, Anniſe and Cummin, were ſo much in uſe amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> that they laid Tithes and Cuſtomary Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions upon them: It's very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that the bitter Herbs appointed to be eaten with the Paſchal Lamb, were not only Typical but Medicinal. When the Church would make a metaphorical Deſcription of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33556:51"/>and Internal Quallifications of her Beloved, ſhe compares him to thoſe things which are moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and uſeful, as Myrrhe, Aloes, Caſſia, and all the Chief Spices. <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> uſed Phyſitians of old, and the Art of the Apothecary was Imployed, not only to prepare Holy Oyntments for the Conſecration of Kings and Prieſts, but alſo to compound Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines for the Reſtoration of Inferior Perſons. Sir, I will Diſcourſe no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon this Argument, only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with good Wiſhes, that your Sorrows may be ſhort, and your Joys long, and all your Deſires may end according to your own Heart.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>I am Yours,</hi> J. M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="letter">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:33556:51"/>
               <head>LETTER XIII.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received your laſt, which gave me an ample account of the great ſatisfaction you gained by my late Letter, proving the Divine Original of Phyſical Remedies: But you ſeem to queſtion whether any Arguments may be brought from Scripture to prove, That we are not only obliged to the uſe of means in general, but alſo to the uſe of ſuch as are moſt rational, and ſuch as have the faireſt proſpect of probability. To me it ſeems very apparent, that we are to uſe ſuch as are moſt agreeable to Reaſon and Experience: When the extraordinary means of underſtanding Tongues cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, men made uſe of rational and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33556:52"/>ordinary means, by the ſtudy of Arts and Sciences: So the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs were miraculouſly preſerved with Quails and Manna, but when they came into <hi>Canaan,</hi> they were to plow, and ſow, and reap, and eat their Bread by their Toyl and Induſtry. Though we live not by Bread alone, but by the word of Bleſſing out of the Mouth of God, yet that Bleſſing is promiſed to Bread, not to Stones; and he that ſhall expect to have Stones turned into Bread, doth not truſt but tempt his Maker; it being not Faith but Fury, to go down by a Precipice when Stairs are appointed: And ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remarkable it is, that moſt of the Cures that we find recorded in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, though they were extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and miraculous, yet uſually ſome phyſical Remedies were appointed, which were not diſagreeable to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Experience: to ſhew our
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33556:52"/>Obligation not only to the uſe of Means, but alſo to the uſe of ſuch as are moſt proper, and likely to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed: Indeed our bleſſed Saviour cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome by his Word alone, and by ſeeming improbable means, thereby to diſcover his extraordinary power, in doing that which no mortal man could do with the ſame Materials, <hi>viz.</hi> Reſtore Sight to the Blind, who were born ſo; yet his ſtupendious Wiſdom was pleaſed to honour ſuch a Remedy as had been uſed by Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians of that Age, moſt opthalmick Oyntments being compoſed of <hi>Terras:</hi> Moreover, his ordering the Blind man to waſh in <hi>Siloam,</hi> was agreeable enough with a phyſical intention. In truth our Lords making uſe of Clay, might ſeem an excellent Expedient to declare to the World his Divine power; that being the fitteſt Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to reſtore a defective part, out
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:33556:53"/>of which by the ſame hand the whole was at firſt compoſed. Moreover, <hi>Naamans</hi> waſhing in <hi>Jordan</hi> was a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Remedy, though attended with ſupernatural ſucceſs. The Wine and Oyl poured into the wounds of the diſtreſſed Stranger by the good <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan,</hi> were ſpecifically appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, although the ſucceſs depended upon a ſupernatural Influx; and the Plaiſter of Figs applyed unto <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi>'s Plague-ſore, was a rational Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, being proper to mollifie hard Tumours in the fleſh, and to ripen Impoſthumes. The extraordinary Pool of <hi>Betheſda</hi> was not without ſome natural Vertue, being adjoyning unto the Slaughter-houſe of the Temple, the blood of the ſacrificed Beaſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mingled with it; and that is by Naturaliſts ſaid to be of a Healing nature: Yet this doth not exclude the Neceſſity of a divine Angelick
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33556:53"/>Influence, to render it efficacious; and perhaps ſeveral kinds of Meats prohibited under the Law, might in a natural way be prejudicial to the Health of Mens Bodies, and they might be forbidden upon a Moral as well as upon a Myſtical account. There was alſo a rational Conformity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Leprous Contagion and the Law of Cleanſing; the Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie did putrifie the Skin, oppoſite to that was Cedar Wood commended by Phyſitians againſt Putrefaction; it was of an ill Scent, contrary to that was the ſmell of Hyſſop, an excellent Aromatique Plant, yet the Cure was wholly from a Divine Influence. The <hi>Jews</hi> obſerve, that though Leproſie be the Finger of God, yet the Hand of man muſt be uſed in the Cure; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we find that the Leper whom our Saviour healed, was commanded to uſe the Method preſcribed in the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33556:54"/>Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to be ſprinkled and waſhed. The Aromatique Oyl uſed in extream Unction in the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal times, was a natural Remedy, though the Cure was attributed to the Prayer of Faith. <hi>Mary</hi>'s ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the Preſence of her Saviour would have kept her Brother from Dying, was not improbable, though ſhe was under a Miſtake with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to that preſent Diſpenſation: Many under Diſtempers expect to be raiſed as <hi>Lazarus</hi> was, only by the Phyſitian taking them by the Hand; or as <hi>Naaman,</hi> who expected the good Prophet to Cure him by only ſtriking his Hand upon the Wall. But my Dear Friend, Farewell, and Pardon me I have made no more Scruple of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing your Patience, and take the humble Subſcription of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Conſtant Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="letter">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:33556:54"/>
               <head>LETTER XIV.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours of the Fifth In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, together with the ſtrange Relation of the Perſon thought to be afflicted with ſtrange Diſeaſes by the the Power of the Devil; and for that reaſon I obſerve the Cure is Deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, but I ſuppoſe without Cauſe; for ſhould we grant that many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes are cauſed by a Diabolical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, it need not therefore follow that the Cure is impoſſible: Indeed it muſt be acknowledged, that there have been multitudes of Cheats and Impoſtures of this kind, but to ſay they are all Deluſions, is very Impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: for ſometimes divine Providence, for reaſons beſt known to himſelf,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33556:55"/>may permit evil Angels to afflict the Bodies of men with diſtempers, vulgar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Lying under an evil Tongue, or being Bewicht, as having no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon the Chain of natural Cauſes. The <hi>Jews</hi> were threatned with ſome Diſeaſes which ſhould not be Cured by natural means, even wonderful Plagues and of long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. There are in Scripture ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inſtances of Diſeaſes Inflicted by ſupernatural Agents, as Angels and Spirits, who diſturb the Humours, and raiſe Storms and Tempeſts in Mens Bodies as well as in the Air: Evil Angels were ſent to Afflict the <hi>Jews</hi> with divers Calamities; and many thouſands in one Night were Slain by the deſtroying Sword of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, in a Peſtilential Contagion: An evil Angel viſited <hi>Saul</hi> with Stupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Melancholly; and <hi>Job</hi> with pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Boils; and Bowed a Daughter of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33556:55"/>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> eighteen Years: When an Omnipotent Power gives leave, the Devil can as eaſily poſſeſs the minds of Men with Diſtraction, as the Swine with Rage. The Excommunicate <hi>Corinthian</hi> being deliver'd up to Satan, for the Deſtruction of the Fleſh, in order unto the Salvation of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, may as well be underſtood of his being Afflicted with ſome corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Diſtemper, by the power of the Prince of Darkneſs, as be taken in any other Sence: As we know St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Thorn in the Fleſh, the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of Satan ſent to Buffet him, hath by ſome Learned Men been In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted to our purpoſe: The Laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Perſons ſeeking for <hi>Lot</hi>'s Houſe, to gratifie their vile Intentions, were ſtruck Blind by an Angel, and thoſe Windows were ſtopt up that let in wanton Glances. And the ſeveral Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons poſſeſſed, whom our Bleſſed
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33556:56"/>Lord deliver'd from the power of the Prince of the Air, were miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Afflicted with Epilepſies, Luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Convulſions, and other Direful Symptoms and Diſtractions, which threw them ſometimes into the Fire, and ſometimes into the Water. In the Primitive times, Corporal Inflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Subjection to a Satanical Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, was the ſad conſequence of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication; proportionable unto the Execrations in the Jewiſh <hi>Cherem,</hi> which we find exemplified in <hi>Saul</hi> after his defection from God: And it is obſervable, that the <hi>Eſſens</hi> amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> when expelled the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, dyed of miſerable Deaths: And Eccleſiaſtical Writers tell us, <hi>Heliodorus</hi> in his Sacrilegious attempts was Scourged by two Angels in the ſhape of young Men, and hardly came off with his Life. The Catechiſts in the Primitive times, that prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33556:56"/>Perſons for Baptiſm and Admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the Church, was wont to be called the Exorciſt, that caſt out Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan: for by the performance of our Baptiſmal Covenant we renounce the Devil and his Propriety, and thereby the better ſecure our Health as well as our Peace. The <hi>Jews</hi> obſerved, that after the deſtruction of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary and Sanhedrim, there ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued amongſt them four kinds of capital Puniſhments, inſtead of the four appointed by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> for he that deſerved to be Stoned, either fell from a Houſe, or was torn by Wild Beaſts; he that deſerved to be Burnt, either fell into the Fire, or was ſtung by a Serpent (therefore called fiery;) they that deſerved to be Killed by the Sword, fell into the Hands of Thieves, or of the King; they that deſerved Suffocation or Hanging, were Drowned in the Water,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33556:57"/>or fell into Melancholly, and were ſtrangled thereby, as <hi>Judas</hi> was. But Religion very much ſecures men from the power of the Evil Angels, and from all other misfortunes. But, Sir, to be ſure you ſhall alwayes be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, if it lye in his power to make you ſo, who is</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your intire Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER XV.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received your laſt Letter with wonder, to find you entertain ſo ſtrange an Opinion, as to believe that Diſeaſes are now cured in miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and extraordinary wayes, as they were in the Apoſtolical times, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the uſe and application of Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:33556:57"/>and experimental Remedies. To dream that Charms, Amulets, Spells, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are of any vertue in curing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, is vain; and that becauſe St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Handkerchief, St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and the Hem of our Saviours Garment, miraculouſly cured ſome in the Primitive times, therefore we muſt uſe them now. The reaſon why thoſe Miraculous wayes of heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were uſed in thoſe times, was for the Confirmation of the Goſpel in its firſt Plantation: But that being now done, thoſe wayes of Cure are ceaſed. How can men expect the Divine Bleſſing with ſuch means as have no natural vertue, as Words and Characters? For if one Text of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture carried in a mans Sleeve, will cure a Diſeaſe, ſurely the Bible in a mans Pocket muſt cure all Diſeaſes. The Divine Oracles were given to guide our Faith, not to tickle our
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33556:58"/>vain Imaginations. I once knew a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Event attend the uſe of ſuch an accurſed Medicine: A Gentlewoman having an Ague, a Begger gave her a Charm to hang about her Neck, bid her not read it, but when ſhe was cured, burn it: The Miniſter of the Pariſh being a ſober, Learned and pious conformable Divine, came caſually to viſit her; ſhe telling him the Medicine, and the Cure which had attended it, threw it into the fire in his preſence; but he catching it, read it: The words were, <hi>Ague fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, till you and I meet in Hell:</hi> Upon hearing of which, ſhe fell into her Ague again, with greater violence than ever, and alſo into deep Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly, which occaſioned her to lay Violent hands on her ſelf. So dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous it is to leave the Methods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by Reaſon and Experience, to conſult the Oracles of the Prince of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33556:58"/>Darkneſs. It's highly unreaſonable to give heed to <hi>ſeducing Spirits,</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Devils;</hi> enquiring of the god of <hi>Ekron,</hi> when there is a God in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> Some mens Curioſity in this kind has coſt them dear, ſuch practices be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forbidden upon pain of Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. What wiſe and good man would ſo far violate his Baptiſmal Covenant, as to conſult with Judicial Aſtrologers, Wizards, and ſuch like Cunning perſons, who by a Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Confederacy will undertake to foretell the Events of Diſeaſes, and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods of Mens dayes, and a multitude of other Accidents, known only to Omniſcience; who knows the Effect becauſe he knows the Cauſe: Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it were the Devil in <hi>Samuel</hi>'s Mantle, that did foretell <hi>Sauls</hi> death; it doth not prove the Certainty of the Devils prediction, or the fatal Neceſſity of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Death: It being
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:33556:59"/>eaſie from probable Conjecture to ſay what he did, there being all the forerunners of his approaching ruine viſible to the World: For <hi>David</hi> was anoynted King, and <hi>Saul</hi> grew worſe and worſe, the Battel drew near, and what elſe could be expected but Deſtruction? If it ſhould be granted, that the Lying Spirit in the Mouth of a falſe Prophet ſhould foretell a Mans Death; it may only proceed from the obſervation that he violates ſome divine Command, and thereby expoſeth himſelf to ruine. Magici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans indeed uſe Charms, and Signs, and Good words, the better to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ignorant, herein being Gods Ape, that as he hath made a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with good men, and hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Signs and Seals, upon the faithful uſe of which he is preſent to perform what he hath promiſed: So the Devil makes a Covenant with
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33556:59"/>Aſtrological Wizards, upon which he hath given Signs and Tokens, that if they uſe the one, he will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the other. And its an Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Dream, to imagine that the period of Mans dayes depends more on the malevolent influence of a Planet, than upon the Conduct of divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: A Belief very contrary to the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, to ſuppoſe an Aſtrological Neceſſity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon all ſublunary Agents by the influence of Celeſtial Bodies, and that the Manner and Moments of mens Deaths, depend upon theſe things. Many have deſcended into the Earth, for fear of uſing Remedies upon the aſcenſion of a particular Star in the Heavens. The celeſtial Dog doth neither Bark nor Bite in our Climate. The heavenly Bodies operate according unto the variety of the Matter with which they are
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:33556:60"/>converſant; as we may obſerve in the inſtance of Twins born under the ſame Planet; although they have the ſame ſeminal principles, Bed of Nature, and time of Birth, yet they differ in Sex, Complexion, Life and Death; as in the Example of <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi> Can any man of Reaſon imagine, that all that are ſlain in the ſame Battel, were born under the ſame Aſcendent? The proper reaſon why ſuch a Child is ſtrong, and ſuch a one weak, is rather to be fetched from the Complexion of the Parent than the influence of the Stars; it's ſtrength is rather to be attributed to the Mothers Milk, than the <hi>Via lactea:</hi> And the reaſon why ſuch a one was ſhot to death, was not becauſe his Roroſcope was directed to <hi>Saturn,</hi> but becauſe the Gun was directed to him. Beſides, Education, Cuſtom, Example, alter Nature; and our ſecond Births
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33556:60"/>divert the miſchievous Effects of our firſt Nativity: Therefore not to uſe Remedies except ſuch or ſuch a Sign be ſearcht into, is great folly, and a Sign men are led more by Indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than prudence, to regard an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique picture in the Almanacks, rather than Art and Reaſon. But though the World be guilty of many Errors, I ſhall be guilty of none in ſubſcribing my ſelf</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Devoted Servant, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER XVI.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours, which gave an intimation of your intention to lay aſide all Phyſicians, becauſe you have been ſo unhappy as to fall into the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33556:61"/>hands of Quacks; whoſe advice hath not only proved unſucceſſeful, but dangerous and almoſt deadly. Shall the Merchant never venture to Sea, becauſe an unskilfull Pilot once caſt away his goods? that were abſurd: There is no action of humane Life that diſcovers a wiſe man more, than the choice of an able, learned and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Phyſician, whoſe natural abilities are advanced by ingenuous Education, ſuch being moſt fit to recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Diſorders in mens Bodyes; who by their inquiry into Anatomy underſtand the uſe of the parts, and taking notice of the Figures, Springs, and Wheels by which Nature moves, become the better able to regulate her diſorderly motions: Beſides, they beſt underſtand the nature of Animals, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals and Vegetables, and can the more dexterouſly apply fit Remedies according unto the ſeveral Indications
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:33556:61"/>of Diſtempers, and Circumſtances of Patients. I pray what reaſon is there Phyſicians ſhould be neglected? Is it becauſe they are not Infallible? if they were, then they might alter the Statute Laws of Heaven, which were abſurd to imagin: As in Religion the moſt Sacred Inſtitutions are ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred inſignificant unto the Souls of men, if not rightly adminiſtred, even ſo the moſt uſeful Remedies are ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred uſeleſs unto the Healths of men, if not preſcribed by prudent Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. How can men expect the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Heaven, to concurre with the advice of ignorant and unworthy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to Phyſick? Broken Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, disbanded Souldiers, Bankrupt Merchants, and the very ſcum of the People, whoſe Receipts prove equally fatal with the Jaw-bone of an Aſs: if one of theſe confident Fellows pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to skill, though never ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:33556:62"/>yet ſome credulous Souls are as ready to proclaim it, as if they thought ſome good Angel, like <hi>Mahomets</hi> Pid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon whiſper'd it in their ears; when it proves like Gunpowder, only ſerves to blow up mens Health. Can men expect Preſervation, when they ſuffer their brains to be beaten out with the Bills of Quacks and Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks, in ſuch a Nation as ours is, where there is ſuch great variety of able and Legal Practicers? It's a ſhame ſuch ſhould be ſuffer'd, who can ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er cure all Diſeaſes, than one; and like the Lion in the Fable, pretend to pull the Thorn out of the Lambs foot, but in the end devour it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that for ought I know, it may not be imprudent to adde one Caſualty more to our weekly Bills of Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and to ſay, So many dyed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs to their Phyſicians Ignorance. The folly of the World is more apt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33556:62"/>to gaze upon a Blazing Commet, that infects the Air, and poyſons men with peſtilential vapours, than on the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Sun, whoſe beams yield light and health to humane Nature. Quacks reſemble the Serpent, pretend to give that which ſhall be good for Food and Phyſick, but in the end beguile men of their health, and a while after the Patient dyes the Death. To conſult the Ignorant, is to tempt our Maker; the curing Diſeaſes being like the mending of a Watch, if not done by a skilful Artiſt, the rectifying one Spring may diſorder the regular Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole Engine. Reaſon prompts men to conſult the ableſt Farriers when their Horſes are ſick, and not take the Hoſtler, who hath the Confidence to preſcribe a Drench. We have many amongſt us nickna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Doctors, who are as unskilfull in Phyſick as the <hi>Athenians</hi> were in
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:33556:63"/>Religion; dedicating their Medicines unto an unknown Diſeaſe: Men who took their Degrees in a Drinking-School, or did their Exerciſe in Fees, affect the Title <hi>Doctor,</hi> though they want the Participle <hi>Doctus:</hi> Having no more Learning than what may ſerve to conceal their Ignorance: To run to theſe men, is as if a man to lance an Impoſthume ſhould run his Body againſt the poynt of a Sword in the hands of a mad man; or as if to cure a Quinſie, a man ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the help of the common Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner. People ought to know that Diſeaſes are cured by Method, as well as by Medicine, by Rules as well as by Receipts. Multitudes amongſt us may be ſaid to dig their Graves with their thick Skulls, and deſtroy their Bodies as well as their Souls by an implicit Faith, in hearkening to ſuch Fellows; if a Cure ſucceeds, it is more
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:33556:63"/>by accident, than Art, as a blind man hits the mark. It's madneſs to chooſe Phyſicians by the Commendations of the Vulgar; they only talk like an Eccho, becauſe they hear a Voyce, but know no reaſon why: and it's as imprudent to chooſe Phyſicians by their Garb, becauſe an Aſs may have gilded Trappings: Many of theſe men have more skill in mending Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than Bodies that wear them, and yet will pretend to cure all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes that ever Sin intailed on the Race of <hi>Adam.</hi> Let me adviſe you, as a prudential Obſervation, tending to Health and Long Life, to uſe the ſame diſcretion when your Health is in danger, as when your Eſtate is, not to depend on the advice of an Attorney, but to fee a Counſellor: And ſince you ſay you are deeply engaged unto me, give me leave to preſcribe the Recompence, which is,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:33556:64"/>that you would believe me to be what I truly am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your conſtant Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER XVII.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours Dated the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> inſtant, wherein you give me an account of the rare ſecret Medicine lately recommended to you, as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible cure for your Diſtemper; being recommended as a cure for all diſeaſes. <hi>Sir,</hi> let me tell you, I have often found thoſe kind of Medicines but meer Cheats, and Springes to catch Woodcocks; and yet men will not learn Wiſdom, until the duſt of the Grave, that Powder of Experience, be caſt in their Eyes. He that will
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:33556:64"/>venture his life with the uſe of ſuch a Medicine, will give the world cauſe to ſuſpect, he ſtands in need of a large doſe of Hellebore: With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, there is no Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can conduce more towards the rendring Remedies effectual, than to be well aſſured that they are ſafe, known, and experienced Medicines, and faithfully prepared by the hand of an Artiſt, whoſe Profeſſion it is, and expoſed to the view of the world upon the Apothecaries file. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of keeping Medicines as Secrets, being chiefly to conceal the ignorance of the recommender, who could not write it in Latin; or the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons diſhoneſty, who dare not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſo dangerous a Medicine; or elſe his Covetouſneſs in exacting, in the price of a mean, ordinary, familiar Medicine, which it appears to be when publiſht: If a Pill be but guilded over
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:33556:65"/>with the pretences of Rare and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, it is cryed up, and ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down, when it's as common in the Shops as Salt and Pepper in a Kitchin: and there are abundance of Poyſonous Remedies abroad in the World, that have nothing to kill them but Faſting Spittle and a ſmooth tongue, their beſt corrective being ſuch an ingredient as wants a Corrective; but yet theſe Remedies muſt needs cure all diſeaſes at one blow, as <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> did the <hi>Philiſtines:</hi> But theſe by raſh ſnuffing Natures Candle, put it quite out. That Medicine coſts the Patient dear, that coſts him his Life: yet many ſuch there are, that ride poſt daily, making every Corner do penance in venomed ſheets; the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for the uſe of them being like <hi>Davids</hi> Letter to <hi>Uriah,</hi> only giving Inſtructions for the Death and ruine of the Patient. Is there any pleaſure
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:33556:65"/>in being deſtroyed, becauſe we are not able to ſay what hurt us? A Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine may cure the diſeaſe, and kill the Patient; and a ſafe Medicine may do much hurt, by occaſioning the omiſſion of more proper and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Remedies. The world hath been much impoſed upon, by being made to believe that Chymiſtry is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct art from Pharmacy; when the moſt excellent Rules for Chymical Preparations have been propoſed to the World by Phyſicians and Apothecaries; it being but a Modern way of preparing Medicines, and doth peculiarly belong to that trade: As much as for a Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor to make a Garment in a new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion as well as in an old: Indeed ſuch Medicines ought to be very prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adviſed; becauſe a Child may do more miſchief with a Knife of Steel, than of Bone: You ſhall many times have Death in the pot babtized with
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:33556:66"/>the name of the <hi>Elixir</hi> of Life, and a Dram of it cryed up beyond a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhel of <hi>March</hi> Duſt, to Reinthrone the depoſed <hi>Archeus,</hi> and do no man knows what: And at another time you ſhall have <hi>Alexipharmagons Panti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magogons,</hi> and medicines of ſuch conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring names, that if you underſtood their natures, you would think them a kind of <hi>Tophet Potabile,</hi> and fitter for Country Farmers to treat Rats with, than to cure diſeaſes in humane Bodies. There is nothing hath more contributed to the Brevity of mens Lives, and the languiſhments of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature in this Age, than the Multitude of ſecret private Medicines, cryed up as Infallible, which have laid the foundations for innumerable diſeaſes, and made work for able Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians: And that which is a ſtrange <hi>Paradox</hi> to me, is, that when a known experienced Remedy is recommended,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:33556:66"/>every one muſt be adviſed with whether it may be uſed or no; but if a Medicine which none underſtand, nay not he that commends it, yet down it muſt go, without inquiry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it's nature, until by the fatal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences we repent the uſing it. <hi>Sir,</hi> I beſeech you interpret theſe lines as the expreſſions of my tender reſpects and care for your Health: one requeſt more and I have done. Put me into the number of thoſe that you count your moſt faithful Friends: For indeed I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>And ever will be ſo,</hi> &amp;c. J. M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="letter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:33556:67"/>
               <head>LETTER XVIII.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours Dated the Fifteenth inſtant, wherein I perceive your great inconſtancy and want of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Perſeverance, in the uſe of thoſe proper Remedies the Phyſician laſt preſcribed. I ſhould be glad I could ſay theſe things to your Ears as well as to your Eyes, but <hi>London</hi> finds me too much Buſineſs to grant me ſo great a happineſs: therefore give my Pen leave to tell you, that the Regularity of the Patient is as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, in order unto the ſucceſs of Remedies, as the skill of the Phyſitian, or the Faithfulneſs of the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which in my two former Letters I hinted to you: And the wiſdom of the Patient is diſcernable, in taking
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:33556:67"/>advice in time, and in preſevering in the uſe of the means until the diſtemper be removed: But on the contrary, many Patients are ſo impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as to follow directions by halves, and yet cenſure Phyſitians if their diſtempers be not removed in a week, which it may be have been contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome months or years, ſlighting the uſe of good advice and proper Remedies, untill Nature be ſpent, and the diſeaſe have taken conſiderable root. <hi>Engliſh</hi> People are uſually ſick too late, and well too ſoon, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb ſaith; and the Phyſitian is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſent for, to try if he can work Miracles, rather than cure Diſeaſes; the time for that being ſlipt, Nature being not able to lend it's helping hand. Many unwary Patients flatter themſelves into their graves with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of Colds and Surfeits, confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſeaſes with their Symptoms, and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:33556:68"/>miſtaking Internal maladies for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal cauſes; giving ſome common Denomination to their diſtempers, and ſuppoſing them to be no other than what they have known ſome reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from, neglect advice until it be too late; and then the Phyſitian is ſent for, to ſhare with the Patient in the infamy of the miſcarriage: the time for Purgation and Bleeding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over, nothing now remains but to toll the Bell: The uſual diſcourſe is, nothing but leaving off a Coat, or putting on a Damp Shift, or eating a Diſh of meat that did not agree with the Stomach, or Drinking a Glaſs of Bad Wine, or over-walked, or a little frighted, or the like: when it may be all the time the Stomach is diſordered with a Quagmire of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt humors, the Blood inflamed, the Liver obſtructed, the Lungs periſht, and all theſe not taken notice of: as
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:33556:68"/>if a man whoſe Houſe is on fire, ſhould omit timely Quenching it, becauſe it only happened by a Boyes throwing a Squib. Many ſick Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents are like the <hi>Babel</hi> Builders, when the Phyſitian preſcribes a Trowel they'l bring a Hammer; when the Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per requires Sweat, they'l bring cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Juleps:</hi> and if the repetition of a Medicine be requiſite, the Patient is preſently weary: as if a wound could be cured immediately upon the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of a Plaiſter, before it hath lain a quarter of an hour; or as if the Cook were to be blamed becauſe a Morſel of Meat doth not allay hunger, when it may be a pound is requiſite. If the Phyſitian throw wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to extinguiſh the fire of a Feaver, and the Patient throws on more fuel, how can it be put out? In vain is Care uſed in the Phyſitians Study, and in the Apothecaries Shop, if Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:33556:69"/>be committed in the Patients Chamber. But <hi>Sir,</hi> your conduct is too great to be guilty of ſplitting your health upon ſuch Rocks, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after you have been warned of the Danger, by one who ſhall ever take it as a great favour of Divine Providence, to be placed in any ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to ſerve you. I can ſay no more but what I muſt ever ſay, that</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>I am Yours,</hi> J. M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER XIX.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received your laſt Letter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you give me an account, that all the regular progreſs you had made towards the procuring your health, had like to have been loſt, by the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:33556:69"/>indiſcretion of a friendly Viſitant, who would needs put you out of conceit with your Phyſitian, with an intention to make way for his own; and indeed it is a very great fault in the World, and that which is very prejudicial unto the lives and healths of men. And it may well be accounted one of the requiſites in order to the ſucceſs of Remedies, for Viſitants to exerciſe great prudence, or elſe by their impertinent diſcourſe they may put a ſick Patient out of regular methods. What reaſon is there the retained Phyſitian, while he is purſuing of rational intentions, and in the middle of his Cure, muſt be thruſt out to make way for the Friends Doctor, who forſooth muſt by all means be the Beſt in the Town, becauſe theirs? As if the ſick Patient had not prudence enough to chooſe a Phyſitian as well as the Viſitant:
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:33556:70"/>eſpecially when we conſider, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Phyſitian hath been long ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Patients conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diſtempers, and hath often relieved him, when the other hath no acquaintance with the Patient, but muſt be recommended to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for their own ingratitude the laſt time they uſed him. Nay, it may be the indiſcreet Viſitant ſhall perſwade to lay aſide the able Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal and Learned Phyſitian, to make room for an ignorant, but bold and confident Quack; who ſhall pretend to great skill in ſuch or ſuch a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and yet knows nothing but only how to kill people dexterouſly: If violent diſtempers ſurprize the brain and cauſe want of ſleep, in comes a loving Friend and recommends Syrup of <hi>Poppies</hi> or elſe ſome other ſleeping medicine, which Tranſlates the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bifick humour to the Brain, cauſing
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:33556:70"/>a Phrenſie, or ſuch a ſleep which only the laſt Trumpet can awake. Sence is a riddle, and Reaſon is a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox to ſome people: I knew a Gentlewoman, who coming to viſit a ſick Friend, much blamed the Doctors preſcriptions, and perſwaded the Patient to the uſe of a Pill, which ſhe found commended in a printed Bill; he took it, and dyed that night: which ſo troubled the Gentlewomans mind, for medling without a juſt call, that it coſt her Husband ten pounds to prevent her real diſtraction; ſhe is not as yet fit to be left alone. I could name another imprudent Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, who being ambitious of being thought skilful in Phyſick, becauſe a great reader of <hi>Culpepper,</hi> commended to a Friend a Dram of a Vomiting Medicine inſtead of a Scruple, becauſe the Printer had made that miſtake, and the Reader not having Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:33556:71"/>enough to correct it; but by a good Providence the dreadful conſequences were prevented, by the Apothecaries refuſing to let it go out of his Shop: The Electuary of Beef and the Julep of warm Broath, is the fitteſt Phyſick for a loving Friend to adminiſter: thus they may cure the Chollick coming from wind and emptineſs; that Charity being better which ſets the Poors teeth a going, than that which cures their aking. The moſt regular Charity to the Poor who are ſick, is to gratifie Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians for their advice, and to be at the charge of their Medicines when pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the Learned, as a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in this City doth, who alloweth his Phyſitian a yearly Stipend to give his advice to any Poor people recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to him; and his Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the ſame, to let them have Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines. I knew a Gentlewoman, who
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:33556:71"/>was conſtrained to hold up her hand at the Bar, for giving two Children a Mercurial medicine againſt worms, which ſent them to the worms, and had almoſt ſent her thither alſo. Such is the ſeverity and excellency of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws againſt ſuch as have no Authority to practiſe Phyſick, that they are lyable to an Indictment for Felony, if any Perſon dye under their hands: and yet we frequently find friendly Viſitants crying up ſuch, when they might better ſpend their time in ſerious counſels and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an advices to bear their viſitations with patient ſubmiſſion to the Divine Will, untill they find eaſe and relief from the hand of Heaven; and alſo in timely intimations to ſet their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in order, and prudently diſpoſe of their temporal concerns by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their Wills. In a ſick Friends Chamber, Friends have an Excellent
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:33556:72"/>opportunity both to do and to receive good, by being put in mind of the Vanity of man in this mortal ſtate, cauſing them to be more induſtrious in the faithful improvement of their own health, and in a Chriſtian Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for Death. Now, <hi>Sir,</hi> that you may be ſtrengthen'd upon your bed of languiſhing, and viſited with the Divine ſaving health, that ſo your moſt mortal ſickneſs may not be unto death Eternal, but for your Glory and paſſage into endleſs bliſs, ſhall be the Prayer of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your True Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="letter">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:33556:72"/>
               <head>LETTER XX.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am ſorry you meet with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny croſs Winds in your Voyage to the Haven of health; particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the careleſneſs of an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant (I mean a Nurſe) ſhould blow you back again into the wide Ocean, and threaten a Shipwrack, when you ſeemed to be gotten within Ken of harbour. Great care ought to be uſed in chooſing honeſt and careful Perſons to attend ſick Patients, whoſe Office it is to adminiſter Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies preſcribed by the Phyſitian, and prepared by the Apothecary: Every of theſe ought to know their peculiar province; for the skilful Nurſe as well as the ignorant Phyſitian
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:33556:73"/>makes a fat Church-yard; and we find that in many Diſtempers careful attendance is half the cure: But when the Ignorant Nurſe ſhall uſurp the Learned Phyſicians imployment, and preſcribe as well as adminiſter, it's intollerable preſumption: care and watchfulneſs are their moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable qualities; but when they are Drowſic and careleſs, it's very prejudicial to the Patient: when like the firſt woman they tempt to that dyet which is Deſtructive both to the Patients health and the Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans credit. Eating forbidden Fruit was at firſt our ſin, when it was contrary to a Divine command; and it now cauſeth ſickneſs, when it's contrary to the Phyſitians advice: I have ſometimes known a Nurſe perſwade the Patient to eat that which ſhe her ſelf loved, when it was contrary to the patients Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper:
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:33556:73"/>and ſometimes the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian muſt be forbid to preſcribe <hi>Gaſcoin</hi> Powder, becauſe ſhe hath known one to dye after it; and ſometimes the Phyſitians preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be all ſet behind the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow curtain, becauſe ſhe doth not approve of them; and in the mean time ſhe gives her Diaſcaudle, and what call 'um Water. A Child once dying of the Small-Pox, yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Care of an able Phyſitian, the Nurſe threw away all his Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines privately, and when it could not ſleep, ſent to the Apothecary for Syrup of Lettuce; and when it was coſtive, for Syrup of Roſes, which was diſcovered a while after in the Apothecaries Bills, who knew not what uſe it was put to, untill ſhe confeſt it to her Shame and Ruine. <hi>Sir,</hi> I hope you will ſurvive this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy accident of your Nurſe, and
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:33556:74"/>live to ſee her repent. The ſmell of a Violet I hope will be reſtorative; and believe it, you ſhall never want health, if it be in my Power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute towards it, who am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Loving Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER XXI.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Underſtand by the Phyſician that your Diſtemper requires Bleeding, and I alſo perceive you have a very great averſation to it: Good <hi>Sir,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, why is it not better to part with your Blood than your Life? but you ſay the Blood is the Life; and I'll ſay, the Blood is the cauſe of Death
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:33556:74"/>alſo, when there's too much of it, or when it's naught, as I am perſwaded yours is, becauſe your learned Doctor judgeth ſo. Are not all Creatures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved with bleeding? and is it not practiſed by all wiſe Nations? The <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> uſe it two or three times in a day; and our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers ſhed their Blood by pounds to ſave their Lives, and ſhall not we do it by Ounces? Indeed, <hi>Sir,</hi> you had better ſleep with a healthful bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, than in a whole skin. Some learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Jewiſh Doctors will tell you, that Circumciſion was a means of health, as well as a Tipifick Inſtitution: But <hi>Sir,</hi> if you do open a Vein, make uſe of a skilful Chyrurgeon, that may not make you lame, to make you ſound, and open a Door with a Lance to let out your Soul with your Blood; for ſome ſuch there are in the World, that want both skill
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:33556:75"/>and care, and pour Gaul and Vinegar inſtead of Wine and Oyl into their Patients wounds. Chooſe a man of honeſty and reputed skill in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and one whoſe particular im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment it is; venture not your Life in the hand of one whoſe covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs prompts him to venture out of his own Calling; neither he nor you can ſo rationally expect the Divine Bleſſing upon your bleeding, which will promote the Circulation of the remaining maſs of Blood, whereby it will the better purifie it ſelf; and the Blood being clarified, the Spirits will become more lively and vigorous to puſh off your Diſtemper; which good news will as it were kindle Bonfires of Joy in the Breaſts of all your cordial Friends: In which catalogue you may ſafely number</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="letter">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:33556:75"/>
               <head>LETTER XXII.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Cannot but wonder, that you ſhould wonder at the unſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the laſt Preſcriptions, when I hear you perplex your Thoughts with melancholy Contemplations. A man may muſe himſelf into his Grave, and think himſelf to Death. To be careful for nothing, but to pleaſe our Maker and to ſave our Souls, will very much promote the Health of our Bodies. The Effects of Love and Hope cheriſh the natural Heat and radical Moyſture, beget gentle and vigorous Spirits, which makes the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Powers more brisk and lively. On the contrary, tedious and perplext Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, reſtleſs Impatience, fretful Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings, and diſcontented Thoughts,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:33556:76"/>they ſtop the regular motion of the Blood, damp the Spirits, and hinder the faculties of the Mind. When the Briskneſs of the vital Heat is ſuffoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Contraction of the Heart weakned, and the Blood grown thick and cold in the extremities of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and is not able to thruſt it ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the remoter branches of the Arteries and Fibres of the Veins, but ſtagnates in the narrow paſſages of the Body and Brain, from thence is laid a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for Pains, Palſies, and all Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick Diſtempers; and then we ſigh and groan, and live a dying Life or a living Death, which is very bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſom to humane Nature. Spiritual pleaſure is an excellent Medicine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt bodily pains, and true Piety is the beſt Cure of Melancholly in the whole World.</p>
               <p>When the Soul is filled with light and vigor, it infuſeth a ſtrange kind
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:33556:76"/>of Alacrity into the Humors by a phyſical Efficiency: Internal Joy, grounded upon the Reflections of a good Conſcience, hath a mighty power both to correct and exalt a mans natural temper. Thoſe Ardent Breathings wherewith the pious Soul is continually carryed out towards God and Goodneſs, are to the Body like ſo much freſh Air and wholſom Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, they fan the Blood, and clarifie the Spirits, and purge them from their feculency, which would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe cloud the Underſtanding, and make us dull and liſtleſs: Therefore, <hi>Sir,</hi> I beg of you, as you tender your Health, pare away all your ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thoughts; and let a lumpiſh Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit be a Stranger to your Habitation, becauſe it is a Scandal to Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Who hath more cauſe to rejoyce than they that have the Smiles of Heaven, and the foretaſtes of endleſs
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:33556:77"/>pleaſure? Therefore ſuffer your Harp to hang no longer upon the Willows, but contemplate the Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of the Lamb, which will elevate all the powers of Nature. When men give way to violent and unreaſonable paſſions, and lay out more in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation than the fruition will make amends for, they purchaſe Diſeaſes at a dear rate. The paſſions of the Mind influence the Humours of the Body: Anxious Solicitudes about Events, and Murmuring at the Allotments of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, ſuſpend the Influence of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Bleſſing, and withdraw that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly protection who hath promiſed to <hi>care for us,</hi> if we <hi>caſt all our care on him:</hi> Hope deferred will make the heart ſick: Eager deſires after ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Enjoyments, as they drownd mens Souls in perdition, ſo they pierce mens Bodies with many ſorrows: When ſwarms of perplexing Cares hive in
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:33556:77"/>mens Heads, they yield more Sting than Honey. There are many in the World who ſtab themſelves with pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning grief, and poyſon themſelves with penſive Melancholly. Wrath kills the fooliſh man, and Envy ſlayes the ſilly one: <hi>Nehemiah</hi>'s grief changed his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; and we know that Fear hath torment: When the Mind is kept in an equal, calm, ſerene temper, the Body is ſenſible of the Conveniency: <hi>A chearfull ſpirit doth good like a Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine;</hi> but on the contrary, <hi>a ſorrowful ſpirit dryes the Bones.</hi> The way to pull out the <hi>thorn</hi> in the Fleſh, is to heal the <hi>wound</hi> in the Spirit. If men did ſigh for nothing but Sin, and ſet their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections on him who beſt deſerves their Love, and make uſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy provided for all the evils of the World, <hi>viz.</hi> a Contented Mind; their healths would be better ſecured: but when any created good lyes too near the Heart, or the Clouds of Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:33556:78"/>eclipſe the upper Region of the Mind, they hinder the vigorous Reflections of the vital Spirits, and render Medicines ineffectual. By me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly, ſad and gloomy thoughts, we expoſe our ſelves to the power of the Prince of Darkneſs, who loves to inhabit ſad Souls, who love Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs dayes. Spend not your Life like a man poſſeſt, amongſt Groves and Tombs: by profound Sorrow and Melancholly, we give place to the Devil. That made St. <hi>Paul</hi> compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the excommunicate <hi>Corinthian,</hi> leſt being too much caſt down, Satan ſhould get advantage of him. Too much ſadneſs, like the Earth lying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der water, makes it unfruitful. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Sir,</hi> let me beg of you to hoiſe the ſails of your Soul, and to bid adieu to needleſs Thoughts. Forgive the haſte that made theſe Blots, and believe that I am without ſpot of complement,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your unreſerved Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="letter">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:33556:78"/>
               <head>LETTER XXIII.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am glad to hear you find your diſtemper abate, upon the uſe of the laſt Remedies: but let me tell you, I attribute very much of their ſucceſs unto the temperate, exact and regular Dyet I find you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve; and you will experiment that it will very much facilitate the Cure: for in ſome diſtempers a very ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Dyet, and taking in little Drink, doth withdraw much of the fewel that increaſeth the Diſeaſe. It ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a ſick man to dig his Grave with his teeth, make his Table a ſnare, and Dedicate meat and drink Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings unto the god of his Belly: when mens hearts are overcharged with Surfeiting and Drunkenneſs, it not onely cauſeth Diſeaſes, but hinders
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:33556:79"/>their Cure: ſome patients lye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually like <hi>John Babtiſt</hi>'s head in a Charger, and ſo oppreſs Nature with a greater load, when they ſhould be making the Veſſel lighter; more being killed by Meats then by Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets: But though you do well to be very exact in obſerving a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Dyet, yet ſo much ought to be taken as may ſupport Nature, and make it's burthen tolerable. <hi>Sir,</hi> I muſt bid you good Night, and only take leave to tell you, that my beſt Endeavours are at your ſervice, and remain</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Humble Servant, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER XXIV.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours Dated the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> inſtant, wherein you ſeem very inquiſitive to know what may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:33556:79"/>contribute towards the Perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Health, and render the means yet more effectual: Unto which I muſt anſwer, If you would exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe your Body, by Walking, Riding, Bowling, Pumping, or Shooting in the Long-Bow, or the like: for by Labour and Exerciſe we get both our bread and our health; and <hi>Adams</hi> curſe becomes a bleſſing unto a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, That in the ſweat of his brows he ſhould eat his bread. Idleneſs, one of <hi>Sodom</hi> ſins becomes a great pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. The running Stream is pure and clean, when ſtanding water gathers mud: But on the contrary, you ought to be Cautious of violent motions, leſt thereby you extinguiſh the flame of Natures Candle: by walking too faſt, you may make more haſt than good ſpeed, and leave your health behind you: Many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple like the two Diſciples, running not out of love, as they did, but
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:33556:80"/>out of raſhneſs into a Sepulchre: But yet moderate Exerciſe is of great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, to warm the Blood, and open Obſtructions, and excite the operation of Medicines, and render them much more effectual. In a Phyſical ſence bodily Exerciſe profiteth more than a little. <hi>Sir,</hi> ſo often as your Pen gives me a taſt of your Eaſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, I reliſh much happineſs, who am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Sympathizing Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER XXV.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>ONce more give me leave as a Friend to tell you, that I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident the Air taken in a morning this pleaſant month of <hi>May,</hi> wherein nature provides ſomething to entertain all
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:33556:80"/>your Senſes, would prove exceeding advantageous, and make your Dyet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drink more prevalent: for there is a Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre in the Air that contributes nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all beings, eſpecially to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a Plow, and ſuck in the cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſteams from the breaſts of your Mother the Earth: and if you can, your native Soyl, where you drew in your firſt breath. But on the other hand, have a care of that which we Vulgar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call taking Cold: for Death ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times creeps into the body through the pores of the Skin; ſo that if at any time the alterations of the Air put a ſtop to the genuine operation of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, do not unjuſtly blame the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian or the Remedies: have a care of taking cold in your feet, leſt you go wet-ſhod to your Grave; or of leaving off a Garment, leſt you put on a Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-ſheet. The humors in mens bodies are toſt in the Air, like waves in the Sea by the winds; and ſometimes the blood
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:33556:81"/>grows as 'twere mouldy, for want of that Fan of Nature: Many mens bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and particularly yours, being like a Weather-glaſs, ſubject to the leaſt alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in the Air, and eaſily blown into their Graves by a ſharp northern wind. Many by long looking out at a Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow have eſpied the grim face of Death; The Air of an open Caſement being ſometimes like the blow of a Croſs-bow. <hi>Sir,</hi> I pray take this advice, from one that hopes you may walk up many <hi>May</hi> hills in this World, and at laſt arrive at the holy Hill of <hi>Sion.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER XXVI.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am very well pleaſed to hear that you are pleaſed with my laſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; but I am alſo concerned, that
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:33556:81"/>you ſhould continue an ill cuſtom, ſo apparently injurious to your Health, as your taking ſo much Tabacco is like to prove: Indeed I am of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there is no Plant that ever God made for the uſe of Man, that hath done more good and more harm than that hath done. It muſt be confeſt, prudently uſed, it's a ſoveraign Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine in many Diſtempers; but it proves no better than a Poyſon to many men, as it is ſo familiarly uſed and abuſed, being in our dayes more taken as Food than Phyſick: And there is no one practice wherein wiſe men more frequently play the Foll, than in the immoderate uſe of this <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Weed, which may not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be called <hi>Man-bane.</hi> Men ſpend their dayes in Smoak, and ſhorten their dayes alſo by its too frequent uſe, ſmothering themſelves into their graves, as we do Bees when we take and deſtroy the Hive. It was a tart
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:33556:82"/>Reflection of a Comical Wit, who being in a great Fogg, ſaid, The Prince of the Air was taking a Pipe of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco. It's very ſtrange to me, that ſuch an unpleaſant practice ſhould prevail ſo much, to the apparent prejudice of ſo many thouſands, who ſpit away their Lives, and drein away that ſweet Moyſture which would keep the Blood cool, and promote its regular motion. That practice which was ſcandalous amongſt our Forefathers, is now become a piece of good En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment; and he that threatned to burn his Pipes, and to cut his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco to pieces, was thought a great Reformer about Thirty years ago: but that which greatly excites our care leſt we uſe it too freely, is its palpable enmity to the Brain and Nerves, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing men to Apoplexies, Palſies, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions and Vertigo's: Many great Phyſicians taking notice in their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, of many of their Patients,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:33556:82"/>falling into apoplectick Fits with Pipes in their Mouths, it being a great Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate. It is alſo greatly prejudicial to the Memory, and alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of its due Nouriſhment, by its laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Quality thruſting the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap> too ſoon out of the Stomach, before there is a perfect Concoction, especially if taken too ſoon after a Meal: if ever it be proper, it's towards Bed-time. He that can give a good reaſon for taking above three Pipes a Day, may very ſafely take more. I have known the Oyl of Tabacco poyſon a Dog: And I dare affirm the Smoak of it hath poyſoned many men. A Noble man in our time loſt his Head by taking a Pipe of Tabacco; that is to lay, the being obſerved to burn Letters to light his Pipe, was the Cauſe of his Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and raiſed the ſuſpition of his being the Perſon ſought for; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he was taken, and condemned and executed: I wiſh it hath not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:33556:83"/>many other mens Souls from their Bodies. Some make it a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether Guns or Pipes have Killed moſt. I am ſure there's no Smoak, but there's ſome Fire. Doubtleſs, if men would take it at the other End, it would do leſs hurt, and it may be more good. I remember one of the wiſeſt Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> ſaid upon an occaſion, It was good for nothing but to perfume a Hog-ſtye: But in that I think he was a little too ſevere: for there are excellent uſes may be made of it: And amongſt many others, it may ſerve for Contemplation, to put men in mind that their Life is but a vapor, and that all things under the Moon vaniſh into Smoak: Except it be the Friendſhip of your faithful Servant, which can never evaporate whileſt he is</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="letter">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:33556:83"/>
               <head>LETTER XXVII.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> inſtant, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you complain exceedingly of the ill Effects of the Waters at <hi>Epſam</hi> this Summer: I beſeech you inquire whether the Cauſe be not from your own irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Uſe of them; and alſo take notice, whether you do not drink more Wine than Water: For thoſe Symptoms you complain of, give a greater ſuſpicion of the former, than the latter, being uſed; ſure I am, the Doctor that recommended them to you, underſtood their fitneſs for your Conſtitution and Diſeaſe, therefore if you follow his Direction, in the uſe of them, I queſtion not but they will have their deſired Effect. I know there are more go thither to gratifie Curioſity, than to ſerve the end of Health; and Pleaſure is more frequently propounded than Eaſe. But let me tell you, thoſe phyſical Waters by the prepoſterous uſe, often prove like the Waters of Jealouſie, they make Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Bodies to ſwell, and their Thighs to rot, and lay the foundations for many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:33556:84"/>as Dropſies, Agues, Gouts, and the like: Many long as much to drink them, as King <hi>David</hi> did to drink of the Water of the Well of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> but men venture their Lives in ſo doing, as they did in that caſe, eſpecially by the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable quantities many men take. I have larely known one come home ſwelled with a Dropſie, another tinctured with a Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and a third ſhaking with an Ague. All immoderate Evacuations are very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Nature: There are hundreds that Drowned themſelves in Wells, that are never mentioned in the weekly Bills. Nature is deſtroyed by all Extreams, too much Food, or too long Faſting; too much Reſt, or too much Motion; too much Sleep, or too much Watching; too much Joy, or too much Sorrow; too much Heat, or too much Cold; too much Wine, or too much Water Quantities ſhorten Life more than Qualities. Many who were only wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly Sick, become really ſo; and that which was intended for a Cure, many times becomes a Surfeit. At thoſe Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters men are ſerved like the Impoſtor who fained himſelf Blind, that the <hi>Arrian</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop might work a Miracle in his Cure; and when he would have opened his Eyes, could not, but was ever after really Blind.
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:33556:84"/>People depending upon the cleanſing Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of thoſe Waters, and neglecting the uſe of proper Remedies to render them Effectual, do but like an improvident Laundreſs, who thinks to waſh her Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen white and clean with Water without Soap. They ſhould be chiefly uſed as Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet-drink to a Purge. Indiſcrect Perſons think to take off the Miſchief of too great Quantities of Wine, by drinking plentiful Draughts of Water; but this is to run Nature out of one Extream into another, and to render mens Bodies more ſubject to Diſeaſes and Putrefaction; like Timber that lyes ſometimes in the wet, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the Sun, more ſubject to Rot. There are thouſands that purge their Souls out of their Bodies by immoderate Evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations one way or other. <hi>Sir,</hi> I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Diſcourſe of Mineral Waters with a hearty wiſh, That you may ever find them ſucceſſeful, untill you come to Drink of that Well of Life which makes glad the City of God: Where I hope you will be accompanyed by</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your true Friend, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="letter">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:33556:85"/>
               <head>LETTER XXVIII.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Think there are few things requiſite in order to the deſirable ſucceſs of a Courſe of Phyſick, but I judge you have had a friendly Intimation of, except it be this: That you would not too much indulge your ſelf in Sleep. Many ſhorten their dayes by ſleeping in the Day, and as it were turning themſelves into Dormice. To lye in Bed untill the Sun-beams laſh men for their Drowzineſs, is an injurious Cuſtom. The firſt Man loſt his Rib in his Sleep, and many of his Poſterity loſe their Health in it. <hi>Sir,</hi> I take this for an undoubted Truth, That if Rules of Religion, Moderation and Prudence were obſerved in the whole courſe of Mens Lives, Gray hairs would be more in Faſhion, Phyſicians would gain more credit by their Preſcriptions, ſick Patients would find Remedies more Effectual, and a Divine Influence would more infallibly attend them all. <hi>Sir,</hi> I muſt now conclude, and ſo may you, that</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>I am a Reſpecter of you and your Health,</hi> J. M.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:33556:85"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
